<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Anthroposophy on Reflections in the Wilderness of New Atlantis</title><link>https://goddesscameo.github.io/tags/anthroposophy/</link><description>Recent content in Anthroposophy on Reflections in the Wilderness of New Atlantis</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://goddesscameo.github.io/tags/anthroposophy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>From Hegel to Steiner</title><link>https://goddesscameo.github.io/p/from-hegel-to-steiner/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://goddesscameo.github.io/p/from-hegel-to-steiner/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://uploads0.wikiart.org/images/william-blake/the-ancient-of-days-1794.jpg!Large.jpg" alt="Featured image of post From Hegel to Steiner" /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Searching but not seeing, we call it dim.&lt;br&gt;
Listening but not hearing, we call it faint.&lt;br&gt;
Groping but not touching, we call it subtle.&lt;br&gt;
These three things can not be investigated any further–&lt;br&gt;
Therefore they blend and become one.&lt;br&gt;
This one thing:&lt;br&gt;
Its highest point is not bright;&lt;br&gt;
Its lowest point is not dark.&lt;br&gt;
Continuous and unending!, it can not be named;&lt;br&gt;
It returns to non-being.&lt;br&gt;
It is called the form of that which is without-form;&lt;br&gt;
The image of non-being.&lt;br&gt;
It is called confusing and indistinct.&lt;br&gt;
Meet it and you do not see its beginning;&lt;br&gt;
Follow it and you do not see its end.&lt;br&gt;
Hold fast to the Way of the ancients&lt;br&gt;
In order to master the present moment.&lt;br&gt;
The ability to know the ancient beginning–&lt;br&gt;
This is called the main principle of the Way&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;—Dao De Ching&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The monkey’s paw of narrative is often that, for as much one wants to convey a particular story, competing narratives tend to be just as true as the one emphasized. At first, this multiplicity seems fatalistic. In the face of manifold stories and frameworks, how can one be &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; authoritative report? Northrop Frye has brilliantly pointed out this fatalistic tendency in the domain of literary criticism in &lt;em&gt;Anatomy of Criticism&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. He accused criticism of having fragmented into a clash of &lt;em&gt;determinism&lt;/em&gt;. Pre-made ideologies, such as Marxist, Freudian, Jungian, and Neo-classical having made their battlegrounds the home of criticism, the work of the critic turned into the work of projecting the allegiances of the critic onto the work itself, rather than for the purpose of comprehension. And truly, this retreat of objectivity into multiplicity, into the mere assertion that one among many frameworks is the real one, &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; fatalistic. As soon as the report of a work is finished, there is immediately a kind of lack constituted in the very conveyance of the report, a realization that the report is haunted by what it excludes. One that is, of course, supplemented by the inclusion of other reports, as a band-aid to the problem. The indifference found within the claim that this one framework, in contrast to these other many, is &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; one framework, is truly doomed to fatality. The reason being that it is an ignorance of the highest kind: a deliberate and premature foreclosure, one that is arrogant and not found within the essentiality of the work, or object. The adherent of a single framework must ignore not only the legitimate insights of rival frameworks, systems, and narratives but, more fundamentally, the &lt;em&gt;necessity&lt;/em&gt; of those rivals. On the other hand, the assertion that &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; frameworks are correct is just as fatalistic, posing itself as a tolerant pluralism. To declare all perspectives equally valid is to neutralize all of them, reducing serious conflict to mere difference of opining. The frameworks are not &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; different, but they are different in unique &lt;em&gt;kinds&lt;/em&gt; of ways. This blind universalism doesn’t acknowledge the reality that each framework is exclusively claiming the totality of the development of the work. And so this view commits a different kind of ignorance: it abandons the search for truth, or connection to the work/object altogether, settling for a passive cataloguing of differences. It sees the multiplicity but denies the struggle within it, the very struggle that signals something real is at stake. This is the fatalism of indifference, where the friction from differentiation is smothered into a formal collection. My very wording gives away the solution to this problem- differentiation of what? In the first place, the very fact of multiplicity is a good sign, since it is a clue that hints at some &lt;em&gt;unitary genesis&lt;/em&gt;, some generative act which created this multiplicity in the first place. And likewise, Frye’s response was to invoke a new approach. Frye intended to approach literary criticism as a theory of literature derived from the total structure of literature itself. He attempted to step back from the battle of deterministic frameworks to uncover the generative principles that made literature possible in the first place. The many are not the source, they are the manifestation of a prior, unitary movement that has differentiated itself. The problem, then, is not how to choose between stories or critical schools, or frameworks, or lenses, but how to discover a generative principle from which the story, and the frameworks for judging the story, emanate, and stand with that which they gain meaning from. This is what I aim to. More precisely, the same approach Frye realized is the correct way forward, applied to my intellectual pursuit, is the perfect vehicle which conveys the narrative of my transition from Hegel to Steiner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story of this or that individual can, similarly to a narrative, be interpreted from different frameworks, with all perspectives holding the seed of truth of the life of that individual. At once, my life story is the story of a musician, the story of a scientist, or scientifically minded person, the story of an appreciator of the humanity, and the story of an unofficial comedian (which probably has to do more with being American than any individual attribution) to name a few. However, once the higher unity of these narratives and reports are grasped, this situation is not viewed as a monkey’s paw, but as the opportunity for revelation, a testament to something created. This became the central pursuit of my intellectual life: to move from observing the myriad frameworks (the very battle Frye catalogued) to seeking the single, dynamic ground that makes frameworks possible at all. Likewise, this ground, or process, in the world (read: uni-verse), is the same process which is reflected in me as an individual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A brief stint of my teenage years was spent reading, watching, and trying to parse the meaning of everything I could get my hands on, no matter how foreign or crazy. I’m ready to declare this attitude the furnace powering my search, and the most important outlook any given individual can have in life. And so I was led, almost gravitically by principle, as rain drops towards earth, into the realm of philosophy. This &lt;em&gt;thing&lt;/em&gt; called “philosophy” made promises to me about how to understand and comprehend the world. Implicitly, it made promises of teaching me that principle in the world that I was seeking. I jumped from phenomenology, to politics, to epistemology, and finally to Marx, propelled by a series of failed promises to teach me, which rather than left me in disappointment, only fueled the aforementioned furnace, so to say. In hindsight, I don’t regret any of this period. It’s for the very reason that I have experienced my &lt;em&gt;particular&lt;/em&gt; past, that the seed of truth wrapped in each encounter developed not only my intellectual life, but the person I am as a whole, and the person I aspire to be. It was Marx, really, who was in a sense the one that baptized me. Baptized me to the corpus of the only individual who made the genesis and unity, described earlier, the sole subject of his work: G.W.F. Hegel. This, in addition to what I can only call a very emotional, religious moment many years ago, where I retroactively describe it as actually feeling and grasping the unity of being, to the point where it brought me to tears, (which is another story for another time), prepared me to read the works of Hegel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-peaks-and-valleys-of-german-idealism"&gt;The Peaks and Valleys of German Idealism
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/4/46/Gustave_Courbet_-_The_Stonebreakers_-_WGA05457.jpg/1200px-Gustave_Courbet_-_The_Stonebreakers_-_WGA05457.jpg"
loading="lazy"
alt="The Stone Breakers, Gustave Courbet (1849)"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gustave Courbet, The Stone Breakers (1849)&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Stone Breakers&lt;/em&gt; is here to represent the spiritual moment in physicality (depicting labor here, but not exclusive to it) before entering a philosophic system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hegel’s project did not arise out of the ether, he was responding to something very important during his time. The response was to the fundamental crisis in post-Kantian philosophy: the separation between thinking and being, or between subject and object. This philosophical trend of Kant’s is known as subjective idealism, and the critical-philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, a brief overview of ideality, and what idealism is, is necessary. I can forgive myself for the brief overview of these monumental thinkers, but what I can’t forgive is overlooking key details in an overview of this brevity. The reason a working comprehension of ideality is necessary, is because the trends characterized by idealism circumvent many of the more basic positions in philosophy, positions which are not covered in this article. When one says the “Idea” of this or that thing, a subjective idealism, or an objective idealism, an understanding needs to be conveyed as to what kind of standpoint this “Idea” is. Idealism, contrary to the notion that it denies the physical world, is the philosophical position that the &lt;em&gt;formative whole&lt;/em&gt; is prior, ontologically, to it’s constituted parts. It asserts that the organizing principle or totality (if all is truly unified, the organizing principle and the totality share a very intimate relationship), is more real, or on a higher level or priority than those aggregate elements. For example, a family isn’t merely a random female, a male, and a child. Those parts arranged by the ideal, or concept of “family” as a functional unity that determines their form and connection, a principle of kinship, shared life, and mutual responsibility to the whole, which shapes the roles, bonds, and identities of its members. &lt;em&gt;That’s&lt;/em&gt; what a family is; the individuals become mother, father, child, or sibling not through biology alone (although it is through “biology”, or the external world/nature that this happens), but by participating in this living, purposeful whole that gives their relations and meaning. The individuals find their specific roles and relational significance only within this prior, unifying idea. Ideality is the active structuring force of reality itself, from Kant’s subjective categories to absolute Spirit unfolding in the world. Any true philosophy has this moment of ideality, as Hegel says below: (And this is a bit premature, but I can’t help myself, Steiner radicalizes this further: the Idea is not logic, but a living spiritual activity whose true knowledge necessitates the movement from “thought”, as unified with abstract thinking and generative process, to perceiving its being, or creative act, directly. This fulfills Idealism’s promise by moving from philosophy to spiritual science).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;But the truth of the finite is rather its ideality. Similarly, the infinite of understanding, which is coordinated with the finite, is itself only one of two finites, no whole truth, but a non-substantial element. This ideality of the finite is the chief maxim of philosophy; and for that reason every genuine philosophy is idealism. But everything depends upon not taking for the infinite what, in the very terms of its characterisation, is at the same time made a particular and finite. For this, reason we have bestowed a greater amount of attention on this. distinction. The fundamental notion of philosophy, the genuine infinite, depends upon it. The distinction is cleared up by the simple, and for that reason seemingly insignificant, but incontrovertible reflections contained in the first paragraph of this section.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;—G. W. F. Hegel, Encyclopedia Logic&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so we find ourselves with Kant. His philosophy emerged from a crisis of certainty. Earlier in the timeline of man, it was believed that man experienced thought and perception as unified with the world’s essence/noumena/being (all three are terms hold essentially the same functional role here). But by Kant’s time, consciousness had become more self-enclosed, the &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; experienced itself as alienated from the external, objective world. And so, with rigorous honesty, he analyzed this condition and concluded that what we can know are phenomena, which are the appearances structured by our own innate cognitive categories (you might know them as the forms of intuition: space, and time, and causality). The reason this is termed the “critical philosophy” is because it did not seek to build a positive system about reality, instead, it undertook the critique of pure reason. It was an investigation into the boundaries and valid domains of human knowledge. The task of this critique was to judge what reason can and cannot legitimately claim to know. Kant’s project withdrew from the attempt to know ideality, or spirit, and the supersensible, declaring it off limits to theoretical reason. In the sense that it is limitative and self-examining, it is establishing a critique, or trial, for reason, that forbids it from entering into transcendent speculation. I was informed by my friend Warq that a comical result of this is that in &lt;em&gt;Dreams of a Spirit-Seer&lt;/em&gt;, Kant is very indecisive on Swedenborg (a mystic who could perceive ideality, or spiritual realities), jumping from “this is bullshit” to “ok maybe this could be real”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This “thing-in-itself” (Ding-an-sich), or the external world, remains outside our grasp because we cannot get outside our own subjective apparatus to know reality directly, according to Kant. You might recognize this perspective as the essential expression of everyday modern consciousness today. It’s quite shameful that in terms of intellect, the prevailing orthodoxy of our time has yet to seriously contended with Kant. Instead, it urges a weaker claim: that because our perceptions are mediated not even by the categories of understanding, but merely by fallible sense organs, we can never truly know reality. We have managed to inherit Kant’s conclusions, the unknowability of the thing-in-itself, while abandoning the rigorous critique that led him there. And so Kant had established that cognition is limited to phenomena. The thing-in-itself, or noumena, is declared unknowable. This created a dualism where thought was confined to the categories of the subject, and that properties are sourced from the &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt;, the subject, onto the object. To put it another way, Kant recognized that reason seeks an ultimate ground, or unconditioned cause, something free from both the chain of causality, and the chain of conditions (such as the vetting process of the categories and forms of intuition) which is bound with the subject in the knowledge-process. He sought what governed the phenomenal world. And so this “unconditioned unconditioned” is the &lt;em&gt;absolute&lt;/em&gt;, self-sufficient being that would complete the edifice of knowledge. God, the totality of noumena, freedom, reason, the soul are all contenders for this unconditioned. However, Kant made this formulation a regulative ideal, a necessary goal that guides and structures our inquiry but can never become a constitutive object of knowledge. To claim knowledge of the unconditioned world would be to transcend the very conditions of possible experience, which is impossible for Kant. The search is both innate and futile within his framework. It is dead on arrival.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although these are harsh words to formerly name this trend, it is properly known as subjective idealism. All knowledge is contingent on the forms and categories of the subject. The properties we attribute to the world like causality, aren’t discovered in the object, but are contributed by the I. There is a split between the subject, which is thinking (engaging in generative activity), and on the other hand an unknowable reality. Kant correctly described the thinking subject’s feeling of separation from the world, but mistook this historically conditioned state as an absolute epistemological (what we can know) limit. The critical philosophy creates a yearning for the unconditioned, that immediately declares itself hopeless in achieving, and so the Spirit of the Kantian is one of dialectic, of restless contradiction. Subsequent thinkers struggled with this divide. Philosophy was trapped in what Steiner would call, a “mere thought-system &lt;em&gt;about&lt;/em&gt; the world” unable to claim it was knowing reality itself. Thinking was seen as a subjective activity, the activity of the ego, not connected to the world’s objective essence, or noumenal reality. Because of this, there was a deep implicit striving in philosophy to reunite with the spiritual wellspring of existence, of being, to overcome the feeling that the human spirit confronts a foreign external world. Hegel ultimately sought to heal this rupture, and would go on to reveal that the true character of the unconditioned unconditioned, the principle in, of, and out of this world, is &lt;em&gt;reason&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Georg Wilhelm Friedrich Hegel (1770-1831), known as the “last great system builder”, was a German philosopher whose systematic work represents the pinnacle of German Idealism, and the pinnacle of philosophy. After studying theology at Tübingen, he worked as a tutor and university lecturer in Jena, Heidelberg, and finally Berlin, where he served as professor of philosophy until his death. His major works: The Phenomenology of Spirit (1807), The Science of Logic (1812-16), and the Encyclopedia of the Philosophical Sciences (1817), were published relatively late in his life and career. Hegel’s dense, demanding system aimed to explain the possibility of knowledge, and unify all domains of knowledge including but not limited to logic, nature, history, art, religion, and philosophy, within the self-unfolding of this thing called &amp;ldquo;Absolute Spirit&amp;rdquo;. Hegel saw the restlessness inherent in Kant’s system and aimed to resolve it by reconceiving the unconditioned. For Hegel, the unconditioned is not a remote “thing‑in‑itself,” but the very process of mediation itself. It is Reason in it’s self-active unfolding. This Reason is not a subjective faculty of the individual thinker, but the active, creative force of the world. Hegel hoped to demonstrate that when we think, we are not merely manipulating private ideas, but participating in the same logical activity that generates and structures all of reality. Thus, when the philosopher arrives methodologically at a concept such as quantity, it is not a category imposed by the subject upon an alien world. Rather, it is the same quantity that objectively structures a chair, for example, out in the world. The chair possesses quantity as an attribute contained within its own being; the principle of the object is not sourced from the subject but discovered in the object. Therefore, philosophical thought isn’t confronting a foreign world, or totality, it traces the totality’s own self-unfolding, including the object as it is separate from us, and the subject as it is us. Hegel names the result of what thought, as generative process, has produced, the Idea (Idee). It is important to realize that the proof that this process of thought is not just in your head, is in the pudding of Hegel’s work, but also in the fact that Hegel’s project can be explained as exploring what Steiner calls a “cosmic thought”. The contrast to the in-your-head thought has led me to describe it this way: there is a “local” function of thought, and a “global” function of thought. They are one and the same for Hegel (with the clarification that this unity only occurs once one comprehends logical thought, and also a point which will be contested, at the begrudging moan of my Hegelian friends by the end of this post). The endpoint of the process is the Absolute Idea: the moment when Spirit achieves complete self‑consummation in and through human consciousness. In terms of the system, the object, or the world, is not alien, but the Idea in its otherness. Correspondingly, the subject is not confined to the finite &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt;, it is also present within the object, since both are ultimately unified in an absolute subject-object identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Brief note on recursivity&lt;/b&gt;: any true system of totality has a moment or recursion. I wish not to exhaust the topic here, because I am saving it for my “systematizing Steiner” project. The reason Spirit must find itself is, because in a system of totality, in a system that describes everything, the end must return to the beginning enriched by the entire journey. The recursive aspect is not a logical flaw, but the mark of something living. The circle is called “virtuously” circular because it is self-grounding, mediates immediacy, and embodies freedom (self-determination). The circle is the logical form of this- Spirit determines itself by returning to itself out of its own otherness (however, the philosopher does not understand that this circle is only the very shape of self-conscious freedom). Since this totality’s (Spirit) knowledge is essentially self-knowledge, it becomes actual only by realizing itself in and through its other. Spirit, to be actual, must go out of itself, give itself form in an other (nature, history, institutions), and then recognize itself in that other. If this remained purely implicit, it would be the worst form of empty abstraction. Hegel’s system shows Spirit giving birth to the Concept, which creates the objective world, supposedly, only to then recognize the world as its own expression. This journey from self-externality to self-recognition is the process of Spirit becoming real to itself. What does it say that this Absolute, God, is capable of creating beings which recognize the Absolute, such that this Absolute is itself constitutive of them? We will leave that for another day. For the biblically minded, the ask of recursion in philosophy, is similar to the ask of Christ in Matthew 18:3:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;And said, Verily I say unto you, Except ye be converted, and become as little children, ye shall not enter into the kingdom of heaven&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:4"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christ is not saying to stay statically in an impressionable, child-like state. It is a call for a transformation of self-mediation from the mediation and lukewarm being of adulthood. For if it was truly a call to the former, the moment man becomes child, and child becomes man, the fall of man commences eternally. Not very optimistic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hegel’s method beings his exploration of philosophy in what is dubbed “presuppositionlessness”. Rather than, at this point, &lt;em&gt;enjoying&lt;/em&gt; the pitfalls of other sciences, which take as given their object, one needs to keep in mind that the object of reason is itself. Since reason is turned in on itself, reason becomes both the instrument and the object of investigation. We can take this in comparison to Kant, who in his critical philosophy, needs a given, a presupposition, in order to &lt;em&gt;critique&lt;/em&gt; in the first place. To think without presupposition is to allow thought, or reason, to generate and examine its own foundations. Reason is being used to discover reason. This “self-reflexive” starting point unveils what Hegel identifies as the three moments inherent in an all genuine speculation (note: speculation here is meant in the sense of “sight”, as in spectacle, seeing as reason does, not speculation as in arbitrary conjecture): Understanding, Dialectical Reason, and Speculative Reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Note&lt;/b&gt;: the number 3 is important here, for the reason that it is the number of recursion, talked about briefly above. The significance lies in its role as the minimal structure for a self-mediating return. [(1)Understanding- (2)Dialectical Reason]- (3)Speculative Reason. This third moment is where the circle closes: the outcome reflects on the beginning, showing that the initial immediacy was always already mediated. The process is recursive because the end reconstitutes the beginning, as justified and comprehended. The reason it is not one (which I hesitate to term “monad” for the confusion it may cause) is because a single term would be static, it would be unable to account for itself, it’s genesis, or it’s truth/ideality. It would also lack an inferiority and self relation, and therefore lack freedom and life. The dyad (from affirmation to negation, let’s say) would end in cancellation, or an endless oscillation like skepticism. It lacks the moment of &lt;em&gt;upheaval&lt;/em&gt;, the moment whereby contradiction is resolved into a higher unity that preserves difference within itself. In Hegel’s system, the triadic rhythm is the logical form of self-consciousness and self-grounding. Spirit begins in immediacy, loses itself in otherness, and returns to itself as mediated unity. The recursive circle, where the end is the beginning made explicit, is what makes the system self-justifying and total. It doesn’t rely on external foundation, the legitimacy lies in itself. Thus, 3 is the number of recursion because it is the minimal structure for a movement that goes out from itself and returns to itself, having incorporated its own negation. It is the shape of a circle that is not empty repetition, but a spiral of development!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding (&lt;em&gt;Verstand&lt;/em&gt;) is thought in its fixing, isolating mode. It establishes clear, stable definitions and distinctions, treating each concept as independent and self-sufficient. The core operation of the Understanding is to assert that A = A and A != B. Things are defined by what they are not, universal concepts are produced by extracting a single property or set of properties from a concrete whole to create a universal, and it organizes the world into genera, species, types, laws, taxonomies, and plants. Bcause of this, the Understanding is indispensable for precision in science, law, character, and art, providing the fixity in the world. It is akin to the goodness of God, in creating determinate enduring things. However, what it does is treating these stabilized “concepts” as ultimate and self-sufficient realities, forgetting that they are abstract in the lowest sense of the word. Yet, if left alone, it renders reality static and dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dialectic Reason (negative Reason) is the self-negating movement inherent in those fixed determinations. Every finite concept, when thought through (or procedurally generated enough), reveals its own limit and internal contradiction, thereby passing over into it’s opposite. This is not an externally sourced critique, just an emphasis on the indwelling tendency of all things finite. The law that life contains the germ of death, that pride precedes a fall, the dynamic force of the object (nature, history, thought). When isolated, this moment becomes an endless oscillation, skepticism, which sees only negation, but in truth, this moment of negation is entirely necessary for progression. In this stage, the maxim of Spinoza: &lt;em&gt;omnis determinatio est negatio&lt;/em&gt; (every determination is negation) becomes explicit. Each fixed determination, when thought through, reveals that it’s very identity depends on excluding it’s other, and that this exclusion negates its claim to be self-sufficient. The finite shows itself to be finite only through its limitation, which is its negation. In the previous stage, this maxim was implicit and latent. Determinations operate in the Understanding as if they were purely affirmative, isolating each category and holding it static. Negation is an external limit (this is not that), and not yet grasped as internal to the concept itself. The Understanding implicitly relies on negation to define its boundaries, but does not think negation is essential to the thing’s own being. It can be said that meaning itself is negation, for what does it mean to mean, what does it mean to exist, than to stand out from the whole? In order to be something, it needs to stand in distinction to unity, otherwise it would not be intelligible in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speculative Reason (positive Reason) is the unifying comprehension that follows negation. Or, if you want more Hegelian words; the site where both “sides” expel their negative coalesce and settle into a ground. The speculative moment is the moment whereby a concept (subject) and its opposite are seen as necessary moments within some higher concrete ideality, or truth. This result is positive because it contains and preserves what was negated. Spinoza’s maxim finds its final moment as it realizes that negation is also constitutive. Negation, which seemed to dissolve determination, is now seen as the very means by which Concept (subject) mediates itself with itself. Determination is negation, but negation is equally &lt;em&gt;position&lt;/em&gt;. The concrete unity (speculative unity) emerges by virtue of the negation of negation. What is truly determinate is not a static point, but a self‑determining whole that contains its own negation as a moment within itself. Thus, “all determination is negation” becomes “all negation is (self‑)determination”. Accordingly, Hegel’s method is not a tool applied to reality from outside; it is the form of reality’s own self-thinking. Beginning “presuppositionlessly” means allowing reason to generate and overcome its own determinations, or in other words, to trace, without external imposition, the Absolute’s unfolding from abstract immediacy to concrete self-knowledge. It is the logical embodiment of Spirit’s journey. The immanent genesis of the totality begins not with empirical facts or dogmatic axioms, but with the most minimal, self-evident thought one can think, or rather &lt;em&gt;can’t&lt;/em&gt; think: pure indeterminate Being. This empty starting point is the Idea in it’s abstract immediacy. From this, the speculative method, the engine of the Concept, is set to begin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so it does, until we arrive at the Concept. I will not rob you of the joy of struggling with Hegel until you “get it”, and chances are if you are reading this, you probably already do (either struggle, or get it, or have struggled to get it). What I mean to convey is that the development… develops, until we arrive at Concept. The concept is the active principle of self-determination through self-differentiation. Being the third section of the Science of Logic (the beginning of his system and exploration), the Concept naturally occupies the recursive position of self-mediation, mirroring the triadic rhythm present at every scale: immediacy, mediation, and self-mediation. It’s borderline enlightening when one grasps the echoes of reality with itself. The triad of the Logic (Being, Essence, Concept) resonates with the triad of the entire system (Logic, Nature, Spirit), and both, in turn, rhyme with the three moments of the speculative method (Understanding, Dialectical Reason, Speculative Reason). This is not mere repetition but a “recursive elaboration”, where each subsequent triad re-enacts the previous at a higher level of concreteness. For example, the nature of immediacy itself transforms as one advances. The immediacy with which the Logic begins in the Doctrine of Being, that pure, abstract presence, is fundamentally different from the immediacy encountered in the Doctrine of Essence. This is already a mediated immediacy, an appearance that presupposes an internal ground or reflection. This transformation demonstrates that immediacy, or being, is not a static starting point, but a living moment that is continuously reconstituted and enriched.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The telos of this process is the Absolute Idea. This is the point where Concept has fully externalized itself (as Nature), and returned to itself (as Spirit), now possessing self-knowledge. Spirit recognizes the entire odyssey, from Being to the complexity of civilization and its fruits, as its own activity. For Hegel, this realization is absolute freedom. Freedom isn’t an arbitrary choice one makes, it is self-determination in accordance with rational necessity. When the philosopher grasps the system, their thinking ceases to be a subjective reflection on the world, and becomes the very activity of Spirit thinking itself. This is the culmination, where the &lt;em&gt;thinking&lt;/em&gt; subject and the object &lt;em&gt;thought&lt;/em&gt; (generative process) are to be understood as one and the same. The Absolute Idea is this self-consummation of the system. It is the beginning, which is the abstract Idea, or Logic as Idea as Subject, gone through mediation where Nature is the Idea as Object, and finally returns to itself through Nature, through the world and externality, recognizing the object as its own activity, and returns in the form of Spirit, or the Idea as Subject-Object. The concretely self-comprehending Idea having mediated itself through all of reality, forms a virtuous circle where the origin is justified by result, and the result is fully explicated by origin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The moment I comprehended a fragment of this, it felt as if a long chapter of my life had finally concluded. Not to mention the point where my good friend Antonio Wolf&lt;sup id="fnref:5"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; walked me through the Science of Logic late at night, up until the point of Infinity, or the time I cried while reading the Lesser Logic due to the grandeur of existence, or the time I almost fell down the steps after being enchanted by Hegel’s writings on gravity in the Philosophy of Nature. The comprehension of the system heralded for his time a completion and the closure of the circle of Philosophy. Hegel brought the old form of philosophy, which wanted to comprehend the world through intellectual concepts alone, to its final unsurpassable conclusion. As we return to the initial topic of frameworks, genesis, and ideality, Hegel’s system can be said to be the framework of frameworks. It does not propose a partial perspective, but rather it proposes the self-comprehending totality that derives every possible category of though and form of reality, from a single self moving principle. Logically, it incorporates and situates every other finite standpoint before and after it in philosophy, as necessary, but subordinate moments within its own development. The closure it achieves by circling back by its own beginning demonstrates that its starting point was already the endpoint in implicit form, thus becoming the self-grounding system that accounts for the very real possibility of systematic knowledge itself. It is a framework, &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; framework, that explains why there are frameworks, the narrative about why there are narratives, and the circle that knows itself as circle, to name a few examples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a strange thing that Hegel’s teachings aren’t &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; new. His core thought, that the physical world, or object, is the externalization of what Steiner calls cosmic thought (thought in it’s global function, as generative process), as the solution to the chasm of subject and object left by Kant, is in essence, identical to the foundational doctrine of Western esotericism and occult secret societies. The world is created and sustained by thought- divine ideas, archetypes, spiritual beings. Hegel didn’t arrive at this through occult initiation, but through rigorous philosophical reasoning. It did not matter, for example, that his roommate Fichte was a Freemason, or other figures in his proximity such as Reinhold were the same. Through naively observing this truth in the structure of reality itself, and systematizing it in his logic, he grasped this doctrine. The content of his philosophy is esoteric wisdom, but his method was public, rational philosophy. Hegel himself comments on the esoteric/exoteric distinction in the Lectures on the History of Philosophy, stating that such a distinction does not exist in philosophy, since the only necessary thing is the necessity of the ideas. One cannot hold onto an entire idea as they do a physical item. Perhaps this is why there is a tragic poetic irony, or correlation, in both the fact that Hegel’s own works were published fairly late in his life, and the grand system contain in his works were destined to be understood only long after his time. This is not in accident of history, but a necessary consequence of the gap between Hegel’s conceptual world, and the ordinary consciousness of his time. Hegel’s philosophy demands a thinking that has developed to its highest power, a thinking that can live within the self movement of itself. Yet, most people, even to this day, remain within a simpler, more sensory-bound form of consciousness. Thus, the delay in comprehension isn’t to be explained as a scholarly lag. It’s testament to the spiritual/intellectual development required to meet Hegel’s thought. His system appeared as a shadowy image of spiritual reality, cast ahead of it’s time. Its late reception reflects the slow collective awakening of human thinking to the level where Concept can be recognized not as abstraction, but as living spirit. In this sense, the tragedy is also a promise. What arrives too early for its contemporaries, becomes the foundational challenge for the future. Just as Alfred North Whitehead claimed that all of philosophy is a footnote to Plato, all of modernity is a footnote to Hegel. Every subsequent thinker has to contend with what he has put forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-character-of-hegels-project"&gt;The Character of Hegel&amp;rsquo;s Project
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The benefits of reading and understanding Hegel are numerous. Firstly, Hegel’s philosophy is the ultimate training room for thinking itself. Since the requirement is for a mind to move beyond the reliance of sense-perception, and to operate with absolute logical rigor and consistency within the realm of Idea, this strengthens one’s ability to think abstractly, independently, and, at times, creatively. Secondly, Hegel provides the most complete structure of reality and details how reality’s unfolding is possible in the first place. For example, understanding the relationship between the one and the many, the finite and the infinite, cause and effect. Familiarization with these categories goes hand in hand with the next point: to reach the peak (and limit) of philosophical thought. Hegel represents the path that the history of philosophy, and big questions in philosophy, have taken. Experiencing firsthand the culmination of this path is truly a transformative event. In learning how to think properly (such that it is one with the object, thought), your own thinking becomes transformed. You start to think speculatively. The final reason I will state, although not exhaustive, is that there is a liberation of Concept from being a dead abstraction. Hegel reveals Concept as living and moving. The empiricist, physicalist, or materialist views are undermined, and the mind is prepared to see thinking itself as a spiritual activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given this, it is with immense respect that one approaches the greatest thinker of the 19th century, regardless of intention. However, there is an interesting phenomenon where the awe Hegel’s system inspires itself becomes a kind of piety, where the admission of its greatness is mistaken for a demand for uncritical reverence. As Steiner observed, “some people can’t imagine that when something in contrast to them is great, humour can also be retained about it, because people imagine one must unconditionally show a long face when one confesses to experiencing something great in a well‑known person”. This dignity often shields Hegel from the very kind of immanent critique his own method requires. This being a critique that does not diminish his achievement, but takes it seriously enough to discover where the system, in its perfection, points beyond itself. For Steiner, that “beyond” isn’t, nor can it be, a negation of Hegel, but the transition from the abstract, logical Spirit (calm down Hegelians, let me make the argument first!), to the living active poietic reality we inhabit. The rigor provided by Hegel contributed to the hesitancy by which I confronted aspects of his system I felt were unconvincing. Aspects which gnawed on my subconscious until I could firstly, finally articulate what I did not agree with, and secondly, until I found an alternative in Steiner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The seed we begin with should be stated bluntly: Hegel’s cosmology was simply not convincing to me. The irony of this reason being unconvincing to the &lt;em&gt;reader&lt;/em&gt; is not lost on me. However, it’s the truth! The more I mastered Hegel’s system, the more I gained an almost visceral dissatisfaction. Spirit for Hegel is abstractly lord. Meaning, there is a non-contestable power to its claim, but unless once submerges themselves in philosophy, this itself is not convincing in Spirit. Additionally, you are free to align with God, with Spirit, and in fact are built in a way such that being and goodness align, and certainly, it is good to align yourself correctly. But where is the elaboration on the work of Spirit beyond individual humans and sociocultural formations? This absence is because such a description lies beyond what Hegel aims to do, and what he can justify. His concern is the logical movement of Spirit toward self-conscious freedom, not the descriptive hierarchy of spiritual beings. And as a result, the cosmology is left feeling very flat. Because Hegel’s methodology has no place in the dialectic for the concrete life of higher and lower spirits, no place for beings who cultivate themselves and sacrifice their substance out of love to create the world. Such a living cosmology cannot be deduced from Concept alone; it requires a methodology of direct spiritual perception, the very approach Rudolf Steiner develops. Only this allows for a freedom more concrete than Hegel’s logical self-return. A freedom that participates in the creative sacrifice of spiritual beings. Who among us, after all, has a reverence for the lower orders of form, of the stones, plants, and animals, because we recognize they are the borrowed vessels through which higher spirits fashion bodies? Hegel surely doesn’t, stating that nothing in Nature is as worthy of veneration as human art. The person who has this reverence can truly be called a teacher, one we can all learn from. Hegel’s Spirit unfolds conceptually; Steiner’s Spirit lives, loves, and creates (resisting the urge to say life, laugh, love, especially in the context of all the white American suburban women who have found themselves drawn to the works of Steiner, of which Steiner himself predicted, funny enough). This difference is not one of degree, but one of kind. No, that it was not convincing to me is not convincing to you, but it did lead me to precisely outline and submerge myself in Hegel, in order to find out why he was unconvincing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hegel’s project seeks to be immanently generative, deriving all reality, from the self-movement of thought. Because its generativity is purely logical, it unfolds only what is already implicit in the starting point, and as such it is the logical explication of a closed system, not an open, creative act that produces genuine novelty. The outcome of this logical generativity is a supremely coherent, self-enclosed map of spiritual reality. Further, the very perfection of the map, Hegel’s system, its seamless logical closure, is precisely what reveals it &lt;em&gt;as&lt;/em&gt; a map, and not territory. A living territory would possess an inherent openness, a receptivity to the novel and genuinely new. The Hegelian will object here and say that the system’s ceaseless self-negation &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; its openness. However, this movement is internal to the circuit of thought itself; it is the recursive unfolding of what was already logically enfolded in the starting principle. This “openness” is the motion of a closed circle, it is the closed circuit of thought&amp;rsquo;s own generation. A magnificent, self-generating logical process, for sure, but one that cannot receive anything from outside its own generative rules. This is not an argument against circularity or recursion as such, as I previously emphasized the need for such a thing, it is an argument about the &lt;em&gt;kind&lt;/em&gt; of circle. Hegel’s is a circle of thought, thinking itself. Contrast this with the method of a Goethe, whose thinking enters into a receptive dialogical relationship with the phenomenon, allowing the thing itself to reveal its law and spiritual, or ideal, being on its own terms and not on the terms of Concept. What you find is that the former is a closed circuit of deduction, and the latter is an open engagement with being. Hegel’s perfection is that of the completed blueprint, not the perfection of the living world. The system is the shadowy image, as Steiner says, or the logical blueprint of the world’s becoming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand the exact nature of Hegel’s system further, we can employ a metaphor Steiner offers: the relation of a shadow to the hand that casts it. Hegel’s philosophy is like a perfect, logical shadow. It’s coherent, definitely, but it is a two-dimensional projection of a three-dimensional living thing (this thing being Spirit). The living reality, which is Spirit, creative activity, is the hand. Hegel’s genius lies in deducing its every necessary shape, and connection. The foundational error made here is mistaking the shadow for substance. He devoted himself to the silhouette, believing it to be the source, rather than recognizing it as a derivative image of a prior living form. The philosopher then really works in a magical circle, drawn by this play of shadows, unable to turn and perceive the hand whose movement casts it. This metaphor clarifies the model Steiner suggests. The network of concepts forms a kind of boundary (he uses the word tablet) between sensible perception and the higher supersensible reality, placing Concept, or philosophy, as a kind of mediating term between sensible reality and the supersensible (through higher faculties). And so Hegel’s Concept and Idea aren’t descriptions of totality, they are mediating interfaces of it. In fact, this is the reason purely mental constructs like geometric circles, or algebraic equations, describe the physical world with an almost frightening precision (to the extent that the less enlightened among us say that the language of the universe is numbers). The correspondence itself is proof that the conceptual network constitutes the structural interface (tablet, aka Concept/Idea) between Spirit and Nature, or between the Idea as Other, and the Idea as finally returned. We don’t derive the concept of a circle from sensory experience, like observing a horizon. We generate it inwardly, and then a profound moment occurs where we discover that this inwardly generated form governs external reality. This shows the conceptual order isn’t abstracted from sensation, but is the formal boundary condition that makes coherent sensation possible in the first place. Hegel’s system is an exhaustive logical exposition of this interface. The power comes from describing the structural rules of the mediating boundary itself, the logic of the “tablet” (this is Concept). And so this is &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; why it can seem to explain everything! It’s articulating the rules of the game board. The effectiveness of its deductions mirrors the effectiveness of mathematics. There is a reflection of the formal ordering principles at work in manifestation, but here is a very important point: this never reaches the source of the game, to the players, or to the act of playing. Math can describe an orbit, but it can never tell you why a planet exists, why it moves, and so on and so forth. Likewise, Hegel’s logic can deduce the necessary relations of thought, but it cannot generate the qualitative fact of a planet’s existence/being, or the living impulse behind its motion. The map is flawless precisely because it abstracts from the living territory to its formal relation. Thus, what Steiner calls the “unreasonable effectiveness of mathematics” (and by extension, Hegel&amp;rsquo;s logic) doesn&amp;rsquo;t prove that reality’s highest point is the Hegelian Idea. It proves that Concept is the necessary lens through which a created, intelligible world becomes comprehensible to the mind and thought. Hegel described the lens with unparalleled rigor, then concluded the lens was the eye, the light, and the visible world all at once. This is partly why Hegel’s Spirit feels abstract and flat to me. When one studies only the shadow which is created by the hand, one misses the warmth, pulse, and purposeful movement, or telos, of the hand. Correspondingly, Hegel’s Spirit is Spirit as logical function, or completed syllogism, not itself the living community of creative, loving beings (not just humans), who actively cultivate and sacrifice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/0/0e/Newton-WilliamBlake.jpg/1200px-Newton-WilliamBlake.jpg"
loading="lazy"
alt="Newton, William Blake, 1795-c.1805"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Newton, William Blake, 1795-c.1805&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;br&gt;Blake&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Newton&lt;/em&gt; addresses a thinker so fixated on measuring reality&amp;rsquo;s blueprint, that he misses it&amp;rsquo;s living source and subsequently, the truth of reality itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us address the accusation of abstract, because it is meant in two senses. The first sense is the previously mentioned logicism, which will be elaborated on later. The second sense is in the fact that Spirit, for Hegel, remains &lt;em&gt;in potentia&lt;/em&gt; until it is concretized by man, as opposed to Steiner where Spirit is very concrete as the hierarchies of spiritual beings. Here you see the seeds of the Promethean humanism that would be developed by Marx: the elevation of human consciousness to the role of necessary “actualizer” of the Absolute, implicitly via labor. In other words, the system is not a map, it is a map which reproduces its own methodological bias in every result. Having begun with logic, it can only ever find logic; having excluded any receptive relation to a reality beyond thought, it can only ever return to itself. What presents itself as reality’s self-unveiling is unveiled to be the self-unveiling of Hegel’s logical apparatus. For now, it may be helpful to imagine the distinction between Hegel, and what a post-Hegelian system needs to accomplish, as the difference between the map and the territory. While Hegel is detailing a perfect map, it is not the same as being in the territory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“In that Empire, the craft of Cartography attained such Perfection that the Map of a Single province covered the space of an entire City, and the Map of the Empire itself an entire Province. In the course of Time, these Extensive Maps were found somehow wanting, and so the College of Cartographers evolved a Map of the Empire that was of the same Scale as the Empire and that coincided with it point for point. Less attentive to the Study of Cartography, Succeeding Generations came to judge a map of such Magnitude cumbersome, and, not without Irreverence, they abandoned it to the Inclemencies of Sun and Winters. In the Deserts of the West, still today, there are Tattered Ruins of that Map, inhabited by Animals and Beggars; in all the Land there is no other Relic of the Disciplines of Geography.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;—Jorge Luis Borges, &amp;ldquo;On Exactitude in Science&amp;rdquo; (1946)&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-problem-of-contingency"&gt;The Problem of Contingency
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The map’s perfection reveals its categorical limitations when held against the territory, or living reality. The first, and most telling, limitation is what I call the “Problem of Contingency”. Hegel’s system positions itself as the necessary capstone of philosophy’s history, yet it cannot explain why &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; necessary truth manifested in the early 19th century. It itself is a product of a spiritual and historical development that it did not, and logically &lt;em&gt;can’t&lt;/em&gt;, immanently generate, only retrospectively justify. The system describes necessity, but its own existence is a contingent fact that escapes the method. Likewise, the Hegelian response is to exclaim that the contingent is necessary in actuality, that the historical appearance is some or other necessary actualization of Spirit at a specific stage. Philosophy is its own time apprehended in thoughts, according to Hegel, and so the system is not a timeless truth descending from nowhere, but the &lt;em&gt;conceptual articulation&lt;/em&gt; of the historical substance of its era. The “why now” is answered by the Encyclopedic system, such that the publication of Hegel’s system is not a contingent event on the timeline of spirit, but itself the timeline of Spirit achieving self-recognition. Ultimately, this is a confusion of explanation with after-the-fact justification. The Hegelian response provides a brilliant &lt;em&gt;retrospective rationalization&lt;/em&gt; but not a &lt;em&gt;generative explanation&lt;/em&gt;. It can assign the event a necessary place in the logical narrative after the fact, but cannot derive the unique qualitative reality of 1817 Berlin from being. This is, in effect, a performative contradiction: the system, in explaining everything, cannot account for its own existence as a lived creative act. It can only incorporate it as a logical moment, stripping it of its vital truth. In addition to this, Hegel’s history of philosophy portrays itself as a vicious hermeneutic circle, stating that “the system appeared when it did because history had reached the stage the system describes”. This functions as an immunity against the genuine question of its own historical genesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A concrete example of this problem was brought to my attention, firstly by me. I was struggling with another problem I dubbed, the &amp;ldquo;Socrates and Buddha&amp;rdquo; problem, wherein I was trying to reconcile something in Hegel but found the solution in Steiner. What I was trying to understand was why &lt;em&gt;specific&lt;/em&gt; individuals become world-historical vessels. For example, why Socrates, and why Buddha? On one level, their historical emergence seems almost contingent, depending on fragile transmissions from particular disciples. Yet their archetypal roles are necessary: Socrates embodies rational self-examination, looking outward, and Buddha, universal compassion and inner liberation. Inner and outer. The Hegelian answer is once again to say that the necessity works through contingency. Abstractly, and logically, this is the case. The essential truth of their teachings prevails despite historical accidents. But this remains a logical abstraction, a retrospective justification, not an explanation. Hegel’s grand “cunning of reason” is essentially a logical placeholder. Found within Steiner is an elaboration of the &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; turning into the metaphysics of Spirit’s agency. What Hegel calls World-Spirit, Steiner describes as spiritual hierarchies working through karmic agreements, and pre-earthly soul choices. The individual, in this case Socrates, Buddha, or a disciple, is not a passive node but a free collaborator. The soul chooses its path and conditions before incarnation; with inspiration requiring a receptive human vessel. Even the possessing of Spirit by man demands the individual’s consent. Steiner preserves Hegel’s insight, that necessity works through contingency, while grounding it in concrete processes and freedom. Suffering is not flattened into a logical node. The world we live in hears cries of anguish to God, the heavens, or anyone listening and receives this suffering as a substantive event, not as a mere contingency. Pain, pleasure, love, regret, insight, “eureka” moments, and more, are all felt by the whole. By subordinating all contingency into logical necessity, the Hegelian response collapses the living process of spiritual creation into a pre-determined script. In Steiner’s terms, it replaces the creative, sometimes improvisational, work of spiritual beings (the hierarchies) with an impersonal, logical automation. The “why” of Socrates or Hegel is reduced to a nodal point in a syllogism, not understood as the result of concrete spiritual guidance, karmic trajectories, and free spiritual agency working through historical contingencies. The Hegelian response thus embodies the very “flatness” of Spirit my initial intuition-turned-critique identifies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second time this was brought to my intention was when a friend introduced an alternative viewpoint: what if the History of Philosophy is actually the capstone of Hegel’s project? In hearing his explanation, it made sense, and I quickly and intuitively responded with the fact that this sounds like something Steiner’s project hopes to aim. After a day of thinking and talking about it, I agreed with him. He proposed that the History of Philosophy is the true capstone of the system, not just in subject, but in its reality since it “describes and enacts”. History, in this view, is the singular “description-enaction” where thought, and it’s object become one. Initially, this struck me as profound, and akin to what Steiner’s spiritual science aims at. This being a living unity of knowledge and reality. After a day, I disagreed once more, recognizing a subtle but decisive limitation. Even in this reading, the practical summons that emerges from Hegel’s history (the call to enact freedom consciously) remains a logical consequence of achieved Absolute Knowledge. It’s still, ultimately, a movement within philosophical comprehension. Thus, while the system can culminate in a transformative insight that bridges theory and practice, this transition itself is still comprehended and derived from the standpoint of completed philosophy. The “capstone” is therefore not an open, creative entry into history, but the final consummate description that logically necessitates a new form of practice. This is what preserves Hegel’s circle; that the end of theoretical history yields a practical imperative, yet both remain moments within the self-enclosed speculation of the Idea. The problem of contingency remains, although it might be a bit misinformed to call it a problem, since it’s more the &lt;em&gt;lack&lt;/em&gt; of something the system can provide. And to fair, Hegel’s project is expressly aimed in solving philosophy, nothing more. The naming of it as a problem is moreso a politic move in order to urge Hegelians to see beyond, within the narrative of my own journey. Besides, even if the problem of contingency were resolved, a more fundamental limitation remains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-problem-of-qualitative-immediacy"&gt;The Problem of Qualitative Immediacy
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;If Hegel’s system stumbles on historical contingency, then it faces a bigger problem when confronted with the raw being of the world, and the unmediated quality of living perception, which is something the logic cannot produce or capture. I will say it again: the logical method CANNOT generate or account for the qualitative immediacy, the raw, sensuous, &lt;em&gt;being&lt;/em&gt;, of living experience. The system must treat the shock of color, the pang of grief, or the awe before a work like Moby-Dick, as mere logical predicates, moments in the self-determination of the Concept. Yet this formalism reaches its crisis not with sense-perception at the “bottom”, but with the very peak of spiritual concreteness: the encounter with a person. For Hegel, all individuality is conceptually mediated. A person is an individuality &lt;em&gt;in principle&lt;/em&gt;. The system provides room for Christ as the necessary conceptual principle of God-man unity, as well as the Individual Individuality found within the structure of Universal, Particular, and Individual. Unfortunately, this Christ-principle is not the sensuous living person encountered in prayer or revelation. The immediacy of a &lt;em&gt;who&lt;/em&gt; is always already reduced to a logically mediated &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt;. The system may be able to generate the Idea of Christ, but it cannot host the encounter. Thus, in its treatment of its own most supremely concrete individual, the system points implicitly to a domain beyond its formal grasp: the domain of non-Conceptually mediated personal being. This is not a failure of Hegel’s Christianity as much as it is a necessary result of the formalism of the Concept. If logic can’t hold the living Christ, what is it to hold? Only his shadow. The formalism described here in full clarity is that since all objects are apprehended in and through their logical relation as necessary, universal, and mediated by Concept, Concept’s organization and giving intelligibility to content (hence &lt;em&gt;shaping&lt;/em&gt; the object) is a formalism. Concept only encounters objects as structured and generated by itself. This is what we might call the formalism of the Concept. Everything must be translated into the currency of logical relations. As a result, the system is structurally blind to the very datum of consciousness, which is the very real, almost startling, given presence of sensation and feeling. This is a point-blank categorical exclusion demanded by Hegel’s sovereign, generative thinking. The map is drawn entirely in the ink of mediation; it has no symbols for the immediate, being of reality. Therefore, it can describe the logical necessity of sense-certainty as a failed form of consciousness, but it can’t originate the sensation itself. This explanatory deficit reveals that thinking’s sovereignty is bought at the price of excluding the most intimate layer of being. The problems of contingency and quality converge to reveal the final lack: life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Note&lt;/b&gt;: The sophisticated Hegelian here might offer a rebuttal, “Life isn’t missing from the system! It appears &lt;em&gt;explicitly&lt;/em&gt; in the Science of Logic as a deduced category of the Idea, the moment where the Concept begins to grasp itself as a self-organizing totality”. For Hegel, this logical category is the truth and essence of life. However, this very defense proves the critique. Hegel provides the concept of life, its logical schema, but not the living reality itself. This is the ultimate expression of the map-territory divide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-convergent-failure-of-both-problems"&gt;The Convergent Failure of Both Problems
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God. The same was in the beginning with God. All things were made by him&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us re-establish what Hegel’s project is, in light of this. It is the exposition of the Word, that flawless logical blueprint, the Logos as the complete ratio and relational grammar of the universe. After all, the entire Science of Logic can be read as an onto-logical proof of God. This is the God before creation. Hegel’s system is this divine logic, self-contained, and self-justifying in all its grandeur. Given this, Goethe’s final lines in Faust Part II, &lt;em&gt;Chorus Mysticus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:6"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn:6" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, points to what the logical Word cannot accomplish on its own:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;br&gt;All that is transient
&lt;br&gt;Is but a parable;
&lt;br&gt;What is inadequate,
&lt;br&gt;Here becomes an event;
&lt;br&gt;The indescribable
&lt;br&gt;Here is accomplished;
&lt;br&gt;The eternal feminine
&lt;br&gt;Pulls us upwards&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;—Goethe, &amp;ldquo;Chorus Mysticus&amp;rdquo;, Faust Part 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These lines conclude the entire Faust drama, spoken by a mystical chorus. Hegel, the philosopher, sees the world of becoming. He sees birth, growth, decay, death, and he correctly interprets it. He sees that these fleeting moments that are coming to be and ceasing to be are not the ultimate reality, they point to a higher ideality. All that is transient, is but a parable indeed, one that Hegel has deciphered, showing how every finite thing is a moment in the self-unfolding of the infinite Idea. In this, Goethe and Hegel are indeed fellow travelers. However, the inadequate becoming an event is a stage which philosophical logic cannot achieve. It is the moment of realization and incarnation, where Hegel by his own standard, or method, must cease. Because he must cease here, the “event to be done” is Spirit’s historical unfolding, grasped retrospectively by philosophy. Above all, as the famous saying goes, the owl of Minerva spreads its wings only with the falling of dusk. For Goethe, the conceptual blueprint, no matter how magnificent, is inadequate. It lacks the power to become an “event to be done”. Hegel’s system is not wrong about life per se, it simply offers life as a specter. It is a chronicle of past reconciliations written in the dried out ink of logic, as opposed to an encounter with the present, living creative act. Its very completeness is its sterility, and what results in what we identify as the fetishism at the heart of the system. Hegel sought Spirit &lt;em&gt;in thought&lt;/em&gt; and found it there. His intention was quite noble and very profound. The intention was to transcend the human subject in thought and align its consciousness with the objective, creative World-Spirit. Yet, in an ironic reversal, he did not use logic as a medium to connect with living Spirit, instead he surrendered himself to the logical Idea, making the completed system (Absolute Idea) the ultimate object of his devotion. As Steiner argues, he committed a “fetishism of logic”. He correctly discovered Spirit within human thinking, but then made the categorical error of believing “that this spirit of human thinking, when developed to its highest power, is the World-Spirit” (GA 108)&lt;sup id="fnref:7"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn:7" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Thus, he surrendered to the pinnacle of ideation, not to the ideal creative source that produces the very capacity for ideation. The living generative reality of Spirit was replaced in his system by the worship of its own flawless shadow. The tool is the idol. Hence, the system becomes a monument to its own methodological triumph, a self-enclosed sanctuary where Logic is the supreme activity of God. That living, suffering, sacrificing, creative reality of Spirit, the very same Spirit Hegel claimed to unveil, retreats into the inaccessible beyond, visible only as a silhouette cast upon walls. The philosopher, being left in a temple of sublime shadows, mistakes the play of forms for the presence of divinity. Hegel’s philosophy articulates the perfect, living plan of the world, but it still remains a plan. It is the Word that has not yet spoken itself into flesh, the ratio that has not yet suffered the risk of incarnation. This ultimately is the chasm between the map and the territory. Hegel gives us Logos in logical purity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/8/88/Hans_Holbein_the_Younger_-_The_Ambassadors_-_Google_Art_Project.jpg/1200px-Hans_Holbein_the_Younger_-_The_Ambassadors_-_Google_Art_Project.jpg"
loading="lazy"
alt="The Ambassadors (1533), Hans Holbein the Younger"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Ambassadors (1533), Hans Holbein the Younger&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;br&gt; Holbein&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;The Ambassadors&lt;/em&gt; represents a world of perfectly mastered symbols (notice the tools of measurement). Yet at its feet lies a distorted skull, or the undenaible reality of death: an unassimilable contigency, and the immediacy of &lt;em&gt;memento mori&lt;/em&gt;. Death may be the most intense, and of course most easily accessible, non-negotiable instance of qualitative immediacy. Every person needs to contend with their own mortality. Even so, it can only be seen &lt;em&gt;truly&lt;/em&gt; by shifting one&amp;rsquo;s perspective away from the brilliant surface of the map. So too must we view Hegel’s logical construction to grasp the living Spirit it occludes. Hegel famously critiqued the phrase “Spirit is a bone” in the Phenomenology of Spirit as the error of misplaced concreteness, the dead end of finding Spirit in the world. Ironically, he did not escape crafting it&amp;rsquo;s logical twin: “Idea [here meant as generated reality] is a syllogism&amp;quot;. It&amp;rsquo;s a great irony that this skull represents that very same critique as self-applied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The consequence is a constitutive, ethical-aesthetic blindness. Because the system cannot host a genuine encounter, it fails before the very realities it seeks to spiritualize. It can rationally reconstruct Melville’s posthumous recognition, but it cannot feel the weight of his obscurity or recognize the divine inspiration (and trust me, Moby Dick was divinely inspired) as a living current. The tragic particularity of suffering and the surplus of meaning in genius become logical nodes in a syllogism, never events to be lived. I think it is fair to call this a limitation, at this point. The limitation reveals its own imperative. If the perfect blueprint feels lifeless, and if the flawless logic cannot account for its own genesis in history, or its failure before a crying heart, then the task isn’t to refine the blueprint. It’s to seek a builder, or in clearer terms, shift from the kind of reflective contemplation philosophy provides, to developing a more active capacity to eventually participate in the living activity that enacts philosophy. That living activity of Spirit which labors, sacrifices, and loves that blueprint into existence is what we seek. Fundamentally, this is what I think is clarified by the Steinerian turn. From the closed circle of thought thinking itself, to the open development of capacities that allows consciousness to interface with the beings who think the world into being. This marks the passage from the philosophy of the Concept, to the science of the Spirit that utters it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="steinerian-turn"&gt;Steinerian turn&amp;hellip;
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The “Steinerian turn”, so to say, is deeply informed by Goethe’s revolutionary method, which exchanges the spectator stance or pseudo-Archimedean point of thinkers like Darwin, for an active, imaginative “slipping into” organisms, or beings. Where Hegel’s retrospective method can only logically reconstruct the concept of life, Goethe’s practice of inwardly tracing the metamorphic gestures of a plant in &lt;em&gt;Metamorphosis of Plants&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:8"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn:8" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and so &lt;em&gt;experiencing&lt;/em&gt; a formal law of expansion and contraction, begins to reunite the knower with a generative force (the generative force of that particular being), which is in actuality &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; generative force. Steiner radicalized this into a conscious spiritual science, where through disciplined inner activity, the observer transcends representational thinking to experience, not just in deducing, the spiritual reality actively shaping the phenomenal world. There is much to be said about the moment of recursion that Steiner pioneers in Goethe’s approach. Nevertheless, for now, I will refer only back to the section on the importance of recursion in a system of totality. Steiner’s continuation of Goethe here fulfills the imperative to move from Hegel’s perfect “map” as Concept, to the living territory of creative Spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is an unacknowledged reader tagging along this blog post: the committed Hegelian. After me “totally obliterating Hegel” and proving he’s crazy and nonsensical and such, I would like to preview a few responses I’ve received from Hegelians, and where they go wrong. The dynamic between us, as interlocutors, is defined by a conflict of totalities. The “Hegelian”, let’s say, is claiming totality, just as the “Steinerian” (or any person whose system accurately captures the “beyond” of Hegel’s system) is. The situation is quite similar to the very beginning of this article, where claims to the totality of the object are made. Practically we can demonstrate the result: when confronted with a being, a &lt;em&gt;spiritual&lt;/em&gt; being, such as an Angel, the Hegelian will interpret it as a &lt;em&gt;Vorstellung&lt;/em&gt; (representation) that must be subordinated by the Concept. From this vantage, the Steinerian appears to be stuck in picture-thinking, mistaking an immediate mystical representation for true ideality, which for Hegel resides solely in the mediated movement of the Concept itself. After all, the true mysticism, claims Hegel, is in speculative thinking. Mysticism for him is a product of the Understanding. This isn’t a dismissal of the Steinerian, if I were to steel man this position. It is a correction, it is counsel to go further and meet the Concept. This is a profound reduction of the Steinerian standpoint. When the Steinerian says the Angel &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; Idea, the Idea is meant in the same sense as Hegel, but as something more concrete than Hegel’s Conceptual Idea. It refers to active, intelligent beings who are architects of spiritual realities and can be perceived beyond ordinary sense-experience. The conflict is surely amplified by a shared vocabulary that masks divergent realities. Here is another example: When Beinsa Douno writes that he spoke to the Slavic folk-spirit, the Hegelian comprehends this as a conceptual grasp of historical and logical necessity, such that a concrete figure (man) represents the soul of the Slavic people. The Steinerian says: no, he talked with an actual &lt;em&gt;person&lt;/em&gt;, a spiritual person. He engaged in a participatory acquaintance with a conscious, guiding intelligence that was not a human. One of these standpoints is a knowledge about, reducing the thing to a representative of the thing (which is quite Kantian), and the other is knowledge of the thing-in-itself directly, by acquaintance. The highest practical example (that is to say, an example in practice) can be found by reading what Hegel says about the plant and what is logically entailed by it. Once this is finished, the &lt;em&gt;Metamorphosis of Plants&lt;/em&gt; by Goethe provides a stunning parallel (although it is not entirely correspondent to Steiner’s project, it is in the same Spirit of what a project of post-Hegelian totality looks like). In one text, a kind of categorization is going on, and in the other, the subject is fully participating in the being of the object.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An issue being faced thus far is on language. Shared languages creates an illusion of common object, suggesting either a need for proprietary terms to dispel this conflation, or perhaps the strategic use of Hegel’s own language to reveal where his system points faithfully beyond itself. As of now, I am currently leaning towards the latter. This impasse resembles the reactions to the Ontological Argument. One either grasps it as a self-evident truism, or misunderstands and places that misunderstanding on part of the OA itself. The limit is not logical, but of the possibility of the subject’s being itself, and so it suggests to me that the ultimate resolution might not be argumentative, but transformative. Requiring a direct spiritual encounter- be it with an angel or Christ or by being instigated by psychadelics- that irrevocably shatters Hegelian Orthodoxy in a way that it cannot conceptually absorb. When put that way, it sounds almost threatening, that the solution is forced initiation, because that is what initiation is, a staged or controlled revelation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The map is complete, with the relation between the map and the territory being that the map is the territory’s logically concluded past. A new domain is necessary to enter this territory as an ongoing creative future. Anthroposophy (Steiner’s system) seeks to enter this territory with the subject as an active collaborator within the Absolute. In light of this, allow me to borrow a metaphor from the earliest part of this article. The great anatomist of frameworks, Northrop Frye, sought a method for immanent genesis, one derived from the total structure of literature, and achieved it. By the same token, Hegel achieved this reality for itself, having sought an immanent genesis of the totality of totalities. Truly, there is no better comparison. Hegel himself is the ultimate critic, having given an immanent criticism of all there can be criticized. His system is the complete and perfect review of the “cosmic text”. Consider a work of immense complexity. A tapestry of history and references. The masterful critic can unveil its architecture. Perhaps he or she can explain how this or that detail relates to the whole, or how the prose supports the ethos of such and such part. The critical act is one of profound recovery and understanding. Yet for all its brilliance, the hermeneutic remains retrospective. The critic can reconstruct the logic of the fall of man in the Bible, but the critic did not cause the plummet. The critic can explain the symbol, but is not enduring the lived reality from which it exists, such that it is conveyed in the form firstly encountered in the text. The genius of criticism is to comprehend a world already made, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; in making the world anew, nor in creation in general. Steiner’s project, therefore, is not to be a better critic, but to become a potential author, and train you to become one as well. The change lies in the move from perfecting interpretation to developing the faculties to participate in the “writing” (as a matter of metaphor, of course). Enough has been done to analyze the divine logic, but not enough has been done to collaborate with the divine &lt;em&gt;author&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In laying out the nature of truth, being, and the general arc of my narrative, there are bound to be accusations levied at me from a Hegelian flavoring. The first is a common one. It asserts that Steiner’s quest for real-time, participatory knowledge fails to grasp that retrospective comprehension is not a philosophical limitation, but the very form in which Truth actualizes itself, and that what he calls a “higher” activity is already the immanent, self-unfolding work of Concept. This is correct, however what is not grasped is that anthroposophy, as explained above, addresses a different activity altogether. Steiner fully acknowledges that retrospection is the mode of philosophical comprehension. His critique is that this mode is passive in relation to the creative act. The Concept’s “self-unfolding work” in this case is logically reconstructed after the fact by the philosopher. There is a necessary addition found in the capacity to co-participate in the unfolding as it occurs, such that Concept is not actually constitutive of that self-unfolding work. In other words, retrospective comprehension is the form of Truth-as-Known, but anthroposophy aims at Truth-as-Lived-Creation. The former is certainly necessary, but insufficient for the consciousness that seeks not just to understand Spirit, but to work with and within it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Sidenote&lt;/b&gt;: It is almost inevitable that the philosophically minded (meant as an insult) will hear the words “reflection” or “reflective act” and construct a straw man to attack as if I am operating with the premature logic of Essence that Hegel dispenses with by the time the system develops to the Concept. The individual capable of laying out the whole path of Hegel’s philosophy; one capable of understanding the distinction between Essence and Concept, is surely someone with enough expertise to not make such a blunder in thought. Certainly I am no expert, but absolutely not a novice. It reminds me of that one tweet that goes, “Little Caesars tastes so good when you don’t have a b&amp;mdash;- in your ear telling you it’s nasty”, only it’s to the tune of “Talking with people feels so good when you don’t have people intentionally misinterpreting you”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another accusation is in the same form as the previous, that the thinker is somehow misguided and not accounting for how the Concept already subsumes what one is saying. “Is Steiner not simply mistaking the acquisition of new perceptual content (or spiritual data) for the development of an entirely new faculty, when from a Hegelian standpoint any new immediacy is merely fresh material for the one sovereign faculty of thinking and Reason to mediate and comprehend”? This may sound devastating, and it is. For the Hegelian. For the Steinerian, the claim that “any new material is fresh material for thinking” proves his or her point! It confines all experience within the &lt;em&gt;form&lt;/em&gt; of reflective thought. Steiner insists that spiritual perception is not just new content, but a qualitatively different relationship to reality, where the perceiver does not stand over and against an object, but consciously lives within the being of that object. The faculty is new because it overcomes the subject-object distinction inherent in sense-perception and logical reflection (and if the position is held that Hegel also overcomes the subject-object divide in philosophy, then at least it overcomes it in a way previously not standardized before). It is a participatory knowing, not an observational thinking. To call this “new material” is to reduce an active to a passive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One final accusation is a rather dogmatic retort. It comes in the form of the assertion that in the encounter of spiritual reality, take Christ for example, the Hegelian will assert that the reality experienced of a Christ encounter, is &lt;em&gt;entirely negotiable&lt;/em&gt; with the Concept, or Hegelian Idea. This groundless response is the last refuge for someone who truly does not understand what is at stake. Not only was this position dealt with in the “The Problem of Qualitative Immediacy”, it is not honest. The full, honest, position is that super-sensible reality, such as Christ encounters, are either mistaken contingencies or merely the raw material for the Concept’s self-unfolding. Imagine telling someone who has had a Christ encounter that they did not meet a &lt;em&gt;person&lt;/em&gt;, but a logical predicate in the dialectic of the Absolute. They would rightly respond: “I didn’t experience a ‘Concept’, I experienced Christ!”. The Hegelian, committed to translating this encounter upward into the self-mediation of Reason, is thereby committed to alienating the very person whose experience they claim to comprehend. Keep in mind, this is not a vindication of anti-intellectualism, or an appeal to colloquial understandings, but a clear signal that the disconnect between the systematic “knower” and the so-called simple believer reveals either a fundamental disagreement about the object itself or a total failure of translation. Both of which, exhibit an ineptitude that should be addressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="hegel-is-a-kantian"&gt;Hegel is a Kantian?!?
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the “outrageous” claim that Hegel is a Kantian, it is not my intention to re-inscribe the problems of Kant’s era in calling Hegel a Kantian. He is not Kantian in his conclusions, but in his philosophical gesture. Hegel establishes the absolute sovereignty and constitutive power of thinkability. He completes Kant’s project by collapsing the noumenal/phenomenal divide, but only by making the thinkable (Concept) synonymous with the real. For Kant, the categories of understanding structure our knowledge of phenomena, leaving the thing-in-itself beyond reach. For Hegel, the categories of thought generate the very structure of being itself, and so there is no beyond for thought. However, this triumph comes at a cost identified by the critiques above. The system is a perfectly closed system of thinkable reality, a logical phenomenology. In this, he remains within Kant’s formal constraint; he equates reality with what can be grasped by the (now cosmic, as Steiner calls it) subject’s apparatus, or the global function of thought. This cannot account for the living, creative territory of spiritual beings that precede and exceed, but are still in part constituted by, logical representation. Hegel, in trying to contend with Kantianism, has produced the Absolute Idea, which is just as much a phenomenon contingent on noumena, as Kant’s thing-in-itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To end on a high note, a salient point to emphasize is that Steiner does not negate Hegel, but seeks to fulfill him. Their projects share a common origin in the rupture diagnosed by Kant, and a common goal in the realization of human freedom. Both thinkers operate within surprisingly triadic movements: immediacy, mediation, and self mediation. This is the recursive rhythm of life and spirit. For Hegel, this logic culminates in the self-determination of the Absolute Idea. For Steiner, this same logic demands the actual practice of freedom, the development of faculties that allows man to participate consciously in the spiritual being that weaves the world. This is a shared Kantian inheritance. The difference is that Anthroposophy is a call to make the Hegelian system’s conclusion into a starting point. In turning the perfect map of Spirit’s past into a toolkit for navigating the living, creative future, we don’t merely comprehend freedom, but actively achieve it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dao De Jing. Chapter 14. Composite translation based on Bruce R. Linnell’s Dao De Jing: A Minimalist Translation, 2015, and Stephen Addiss and Stanley Lombardo’s Lao-tzu: Tao Te Ching, Hackett Publishing, 1993, p. 14.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frye, Northrop. Anatomy of Criticism: Four Essays. Princeton UP, 1957.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hegel, Georg Wilhelm Friedrich. Encyclopedia of the Philosophical Sciences in Basic Outline. Part I: Science of Logic. Specifically, §95 on the &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.hegel.net" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.hegel.net&lt;/a&gt; website.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bible. King James Version&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://empyreantrail.wordpress.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://empyreantrail.wordpress.com&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von. &amp;ldquo;Chorus Mysticus.&amp;rdquo; Faust, Part Two. Translated by Philip Wayne. Penguin Classics, 1959. LiederNet Archive, &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.lieder.net/lieder/get_text.html?TextId=49341" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;www.lieder.net/lieder/get_text.html?TextId=49341&lt;/a&gt;. Accessed 10 Dec. 2025.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:6" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:7"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steiner, Rudolf. Goethes Weltanschauung. Rudolf Steiner Verlag, 1979. Gesamtausgabe (GA), vol. 6.
&lt;br&gt;&amp;mdash;. Die Philosophie der Freiheit. Rudolf Steiner Verlag, 1978. Gesamtausgabe (GA), vol. 4.
&lt;br&gt;&amp;mdash;. Von Jesus zu Christus. Rudolf Steiner Verlag, 1989. Gesamtausgabe (GA), vol. 108.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:7" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:8"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von. Die Metamorphose der Pflanzen / The Metamorphosis of Plants. Edited by Gordon L. Miller, Getrud W. Miller, MIT Press, 2009.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:8" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Problem of Africa in German Idealism and Anthroposophy's Treatment as a Response to Afro-Pessimism</title><link>https://goddesscameo.github.io/p/the-problem-of-africa-in-german-idealism-and-anthroposophys-treatment-as-a-response-to-afro-pessimism/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://goddesscameo.github.io/p/the-problem-of-africa-in-german-idealism-and-anthroposophys-treatment-as-a-response-to-afro-pessimism/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/3/35/1375_Atlas_Catalan_Abraham_Cresques.jpg/2560px-1375_Atlas_Catalan_Abraham_Cresques.jpg" alt="Featured image of post The Problem of Africa in German Idealism and Anthroposophy's Treatment as a Response to Afro-Pessimism" /&gt;&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Philosophy’s consideration is supposedly one which is both universally accessible, and universally accepting of contribution. There is an imperative for any valid domain that it be accessible to anyone regardless of background, and for this domain to relate back onto man, in such a way as to be receptive to the background of the contributing agent. As such, the question of how the domain of philosophy stands to exclude is not simply a sociological critique, but it itself a philosophical problem that strikes at its claim to truth, and it’s status as a valid domain. Nowhere is this problem more acute, or more personal for me as a thinker who happens to be African American, than in the tradition of German Idealism, and supposedly its indirect successor found in Rudolf Steiner’s Anthroposophy. In the works of Kant and Hegel, and in the spiritual-scientific system of Steiner, we find some of the most powerful frameworks ever conceived for understanding freedom, humanity, consciousness, etc. Frameworks that &lt;em&gt;explicitly&lt;/em&gt; aspire to universality and objectivity. Yet, embedded within these same works are characterizations of Africa and its people that range from apparent prejudiced ignorance to a placement “outside of History”. This creates quite a few seeming tensions, and conjured within me questions, which I have since reconciled, but wish for the reader to keep in mind in order to guide their own thinking and arrive at well-reasoned conclusions. Indeed, it only takes a few Google searches to come across the scathing words Kant and Hegel have had for an entire continent and groups of people. What differentiates them from their contemporaries, found in individuals like Linnaeus, if anything? How can such totalizing systems be so exclusionary? When we get to the more esoteric frameworks, such as with Anthroposophy, in what way are such thinkers (or in this case, “seers” perhaps) not essentializing the categories employed during their time and placing a kind of determinism upon individuals which are within categories? How are the individual and the particular group they belong to reconciled, what is that relationship? These questions go on and on, however the most important question guiding inquiry is this: how can one value the architecture of a system seemingly built, at least in part, with flawed and exclusionary materials? In other words, where do the descriptions of Africa, and this “race” of people (Africans), come from, and what does it stand to mean for the destiny of these people according to such philosophers and why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The contemporary philosophical movement of Afro-pessimism offers a stark and logical response. “One cannot value such systems” is essentially the insight of thinkers like Frank B. Wilderson III. The standpoint of Afro-pessimism (hereby referred to as AP) is that this &lt;em&gt;thing&lt;/em&gt; called blackness is not just excluded from, but is the constitutive outside against which Western concepts of “Humanity” and “Social Life” are defined. From this view, the problem of Africa in Kant, Hegel, and what appears to be Steiner is not an accidental flaw, but the revealing symptom of a structural antagonism. To seek inclusion or reclamation within their systems is, therefore, a kind of fundamental error. This article argues against that conclusion. What I propose is that the most rigorous response to this historical problem is not to discard these philosophical systems, but to engage in an immanent critique and subsequent reclamation, if appropriate. By carefully comprehending the claimed universal method of these thinkers and then appraising the claims they make, such as with Africa, one can correctly avoid “throwing out the baby with the bathwater”, as a matter of saying. If such contingent particularities of their historical consciousness exist and pervade their thought, we can successfully discover how, using their own logic, they themselves contain the resources for self-correction. Through an examination of Hegel’s claims, Steiner’s understanding of what “race” even is, and finally, the universal imperatives at the core of these projects, the solution does not lie in the aptly named pessimistic, self-destructive passivity of AP. If a solution exists, it exists within clarifying the universality these thinkers left behind as the inheritance of all mankind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="universal-systems-particular-blindness"&gt;Universal Systems, Particular Blindness
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Universal aspirations of European philosophy from the colonial period (let us say from the 1600s to the 1800s) did not emerge in a vacuum. They were conceived in a world being reshaped by colonial conquest, slavery, resource extraction, and so on and so forth. These are all second-order, or for the philosophically minded, conditional factors. I don’t mean to invoke “material conditions”, since this would be making a very huge blunder in grounding necessity. Rather, I would like to place the necessity within the mode of consciousness which came to dominate the West. Colonialism is not &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; the economic “machine”, it is &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; the expression of the intellectual current of the age, one which seeks to master the external world through abstraction, quantification, and mechanism, and to sever the human being from the living connection to its spiritual origins, and crystallize this spirit into a fixed logical system. This is the consciousness that built not only the steam engine and the stock market, but also the philosophical systems of Kant and Hegel. Kant’s critical philosophy, which aimed to find the universal laws of pure reason, and Hegel’s Absolute Idea, which comprehended reality as the logical system of Concept, are supreme intellectual achievements of this current. They represent the peak of mind&amp;rsquo;s capacity to create self-enclosed, rational universes. It’s therefore not a historical coincidence that this epoch of radical abstraction in thought coincided with the project of global abstraction in practice, otherwise known as colonialism. The same consciousness that reduced the world to categories and concept &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; reduced foreign lands to territories with qualities removed. Philosopher’s like John Locke, who theorized on property while helping draft the slave constitutions of Caroline, and John Stuart Mill, who defended liberty while administering the British Empire, were not hypocrites. They were thinkers whose insights into law, liberty, and individuality were shaped by, and in turn gave form to, this dominant, globalizing, and ultimately abstracting mode of consciousness. Their work reveals that the very concepts of modern Western freedom and universality were, from their inception, entangled with the logic of domination and exclusion required by the global system they helped to rationalize. This entanglement is evident not only in whom these philosophies excluded, but in the very conception of “individual” which was promoted. The subject afforded rights by Locke, or moral consideration by Kant (with a qualification we will get to) was a specific historical abstraction- this being the propertied, European male. This model of subjectivity was already a fiction, a selective elevation of one mode of being into a universal form. Yet, this fiction did not culminate in a true qualitative individuality universally. Nor would it be possible to rescue such a project, let alone aim to integrate into it. Instead, under the logic of the modern, abstracting consciousness they helped codify, the particular “Caucasian” subject has dissolved just as surely as the colonized “other”. What has emerged is not a universal qualitative individuality, but the quantified fungible unit. It is the interchangeable “man” of bureaucracy and markets, the “mass man” of José Ortega y Gasset, and the &lt;em&gt;One-Dimensional Man&lt;/em&gt; of Herbert Marcuse. Fundamentally, it is the unfree individual. The philosophical projects of Locke and the like thus contain a tension. Their abstractions point toward a universal humanity, yet their historical instantiation served a particular, exclusionary order. At best, this means their philosophies are on some level incomplete as a result of a contingent birth untranscended. At worst, it suggests that the logic of abstraction, of the modernity which they contain, has in it from the very beginning a reduction of the human to a manageable quantity. This is the very possibility that enables both the rationalized “liberty” of the citizen and the rationalized exploitation of the colony.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Immanuel Kant’s work presents such a striking internal conflict between his groundbreaking universal ethics via the Categorical Imperative, and his own deeply held prejudices. In his writings &lt;em&gt;Observations on the Feeling of the Beautiful and Sublime&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Groundwork of Metaphysics of Morals&lt;/em&gt;, Kant writes, for instance, that the “Negroes of Africa” had received “by nature no feeling that rises above the trifling”. He goes so far as to tie moral character with biology, providing pseudo-scientific justifications for purported suitability for servitude. This was certainly not a marginal aside. It can be read rightly as a systematic attempt to ground human difference in natural law, directly contradicting the core principle he would later establish as the foundation of morality: that &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; rational being possesses an incalculable worth as an end in itself, as noumena.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let it be known that this schema was not left unchallenged within Kant’s time. The philosopher was directly critiqued by a rigorous empiricist found within Johan Georg Forster. Forster, who had sailed with Captain James Cook on his famous voyage, wrote to Kant, correcting his blatantly wrong empirical commentary on non-European peoples. Forester’s first-hand observations from &lt;em&gt;A Voyage Round the World&lt;/em&gt; presented a far more complex and human picture of Pacific and other indigenous societies, undermining the simplistic racial categories invoked by Kant. Within this encounter, one can observe a dynamic of the abstracting, classifying impulse of the foot soldier of modernity (in this case, Kant), being confronted by the concrete, experiential knowledge of the traveler-scientist (Forster). However, we too would be guilty of not affording another subjectivity, if we did not recognize Kant’s own evolution in thought. His later shift, particularly in &lt;em&gt;The Metaphysics of Morals&lt;/em&gt;, surely can be described as a change of heart, but it is also Kant being compelled into self-correction by the logic of his own system. In this text, here, the philosopher who once catalogued racial destinies just 10 years earlier, comes around and condemns the institutions of non-European slavery, de-links moral character with biology, etc. He now constructs an edifice of right (Recht) that methodically excludes such empirical classifications, and condemns slavery as a fundamental violation of the Categorical Imperative. Slavery treats a person as a mere means rather than as an end (in this case, as a rational being), and so would make Kant the biggest hypocrite if allowing for such an acceptance. Moreover, it would mean he is failing by the very same standard that &lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt; set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what prompted this move? The move which severed moral worth from any biological contingency has established the universal “person”. Anyone who is subject to moral law is defined solely by the possession of practical reason, a faculty which, in Kant’s mature philosophy, admits no gradation by skin color. What prompted this move, is a demonstration of our initial claim of universality, if true, having the tools to rescue itself. The power of a truly universalizing philosophical system outgrows the flawed particular inputs of its author. Kant’s early racism was stupid, not just ethically, but philosophically, as a non-universalizable particular that could not withstand the formal test of his own categorical imperative. His later work shows the system expunging itself of this incoherence. The abstract drive for a perfectly rational system proved stronger than the empirical prejudices it initially absorbed. In Kant, we see the modern consciousness beginning to confront, and correct, its own exclusionary logic from within.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="hegels-africa"&gt;Hegel&amp;rsquo;s Africa
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In terms of empirical contingency, Hegel’s &lt;em&gt;system&lt;/em&gt; offers no such drawback. Within the majority of his work (barre what we will soon discuss), what you find is the lofty heights of abstract thought, the pure movement of the Concept. In other words, he arrives at his system deductively, unable to be tainted by empirical matters. This is precisely the appeal of his system, the fact that it demonstrates &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; what is necessary in logical form. His “racism”, so-called, is therefore a different order than Kant’s. It cannot be a biological prejudice smuggled into anthropology, because the very structure of his philosophy precludes biology, or nature, from determining or overdetermining Spirit (here to be read as the active principle of totality). Where Kant imports empirical racial hierarchies into his philosophy, Hegel’s Science of Logic (and Phenomenology of Spirit, although this does not offer any sort of key to understanding his thought and comes quite late in his system) develops a framework where Spirit is a universal potentiality. What this means is that there is no reality where biology, or any other contingency, effects the internality of a thing. Moral worth, in this context, can never be tied to biological characteristics. In a very rough manner, the opposite can be said, that the internality is what shapes the externality. However, this lends itself to needing qualifications and inviting misinterpretations, so it is better left unsaid. Regardless, what is to be emphasized is the universality of Spirit. This is why Hegel’s infamous placement of Africa “outside the compass of history” in the &lt;em&gt;Lectures on the Philosophy of History&lt;/em&gt; must be read not as a racial slur, but as a specific claim within his system. For Hegel, “History” is a technical term denoting the process wherein Spirit achieves self-conscious freedom and externalizes that freedom in the rational, universal form of the State. His assessment of Africa is thus a philosophical judgment about the development of a specific form of political self-consciousness. What meets the standard of entering “History” for Hegel, is for a people to find a universality, and spread it. This universality is a self-conscious universality (meaning there is a mechanism of self-recognition) where freedom is law and vice versa, embodied in the rational state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The very existence of concepts like &lt;em&gt;Ubuntu&lt;/em&gt;, which articulates a conception of mutual recognition, demonstrates that many African civilizations already contain, at least implicitly, a seed of universality. African civilizations had, and have, a substance. All people do. What&amp;rsquo;s lacking is full actualization through the form of a rational state and codified law. Every man on earth is self-conscious and relates objectively to others within a group. But for a people to come together and form a state — one that recursively enforces and mediates universal principles of right — requires the collective recognition of freedom as law and law as freedom. In other words, African kingdoms had laws and governance surely, so ethical substance is not lacking. The objective institutions of a rational modern state were for Hegel. This state is defined by its capacity to recognize all subjects as abstract, right-bearing individuals before a universal law, rather than as members of a particular family, clan, or tribe. This is the transition from customary governance to constitutional right. Now that the standard is clarified for Hegel, this methodology explains his otherwise surprising engagement with the continent. Unlike the broad, derogatory brush of his peers, Hegel demonstrates a specific (if not flawed and limited) interest in African societies, referencing Ashanti and Dahomey. He is attempting to analyze them through his conceptual framework rather than dismiss them outright. His framework even possesses a logical aperture for recognizing Black political agency, most notably in his positive commentary on the Haitian Revolution, where he acknowledges enslaved Africans attaining a “concept of freedom” and forming a state. Such commentary shows, in principle, that his system could register and explain such an event as a moment of world historical significance, even if he did not place it central to his narrative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it relates to the claim that the African has not achieved the necessary “distinction between himself as an individual and the universality of his essential being”, Hegel is correct on this specific, developmental point. The sharp differentiation of the individual ego from the communal and natural whole represents an advancement of stage in the evolution of consciousness. This is the truth within his Eurocentrism. However, this should not be mistaken for a prescription of the future. It’s a &lt;em&gt;description&lt;/em&gt; of a formal stage which aligns with the development of Concept, or in other words, vindicates the deductive result of Concept’s developmental path by finding it in the world. To observe that a particular form of consciousness has not yet emerged is not to predict it cannot or will not. Hegel’s own comments on Haiti (such as written on by Susan Buck-Morss&amp;rsquo;s Hegel, Haiti, and Universal History) should dispel the notion that “Africans” will never amount to anything, designated into an eternal state of nature. In fact, his own methodology teaches that every stage is necessarily overcome. It is a fact that every subsequent development of what Hegel calls “history” becomes the standard, lest it be destroyed by the truth of a further developed concept. What is claimed as the “standard” or the pinnacle of development &lt;em&gt;must be&lt;/em&gt;, in some way or another, adopted by all states unless they face destruction. Consider this metaphor: when playing video games, META is defined as the most efficient tactic available. Such a tactic is a novelty of action, if only to be replaced by another META. In order to succeed at the “game”, you either have to adopt this “META” strategy, or come up with ways to confront it, lest you lose the game. This is essentially what has happened with the state form and consciousness found in Europe and the resulting reaction by the world that we call “modernity”. It follows, then, that a more “developed” logical structure does not equate to a higher human worth or a “better” humanity. It only describes a capacity for a certain kind of abstract reflection and institutional formation at the time of description.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hegel is right, in concept, about these aspects of Africa. However, having established that the concept of state is a logical deduction, we must now confront the disquieting reality of his &lt;em&gt;Philosophy of History&lt;/em&gt; lectures. Here, the unspoiled movements of the concept collides with the dirty, prejudiced empirical data of its time. In order to appraise world history, we need to use empirical data to trace the concept’s actualization in the world. We wouldn’t want it to remain an abstract schema floating in the sky, unable to enlighten us about what &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;. This integration with empirical data certainly doesn’t invalidate the deductive aspect of his system, but it does point to a failure in structural integrity, where philosophy is being supplied with biased missionary reports and colonial-era anthropology. You know, the kind of secondary literature available to a German professor in the 1820s, and so steeped in the racial ideologies of their time. As a result, when declaring “Africa” no historical part of the world, it is just as much validating a pre-existing colonial narrative with the authority of philosophy, as it is pronouncing a logical conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lectures present a series of mistakes, each fueling the next. The first is Hegel’s description of the African interior as an “unknown Upland” with no internal movement, where the “Negroes have seldom made their way through”. Such a geographical error erases the millennia of complex history including Bantu migrations, the trans-Saharan trade networks which linked Timbuktu to the Mediterranean, the dynamic empires of Ghana, Mali, Songhai, etc. By rendering Africa geographically static, he manufactures the precondition for declaring it &lt;em&gt;historically&lt;/em&gt; stagnant, missing the very same logical movements his own Science of Logic should have recognized as its own. The lectures traffic in sweeping, dehumanizing claims. Africa as a whole is painted as a place where cannibalism is customary, parents and children sell each other regularly, and there is “perfect contempt for humanity”, to quote Hegel. These tropes are drawn from the most sensationalistic and context-stripped missionary reports as the normative character of the race, when in reality, these were atrocities of war or famine. Philosophically, this serves the function of manufacturing an empirical proof that Africans exist in a state of mere sensuous volition, devoid of “universal spiritual laws” (like familial morality) that form the ethical substance from which the State immanently emerges. The brutalizing effects of the Trans-Atlantic Slave trade (which he &lt;em&gt;notes&lt;/em&gt;) are then simplified as the essentiality of an entire continent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The analysis of the “African religion” is just as much a failure. Most noteworthy is the fact that complex monotheistic and cosmological systems, such as Akan Nyame, existed. Cosmic systems are reduced into sorcery and fetishism, arguing that the African “commands the elements” and thus has no “consciousness of a Higher Power”. Additionally, he describes the ritual interaction with objects. In claiming, “if any mischance occurs… they bind and beat or destroy the Fetich”, what he effectively does is interpret a ritual interaction with a mediating vessel of spiritual force as literal transactional mastery over a powerless object. From the standpoint of abstract intellectualism, such an act indeed seems nonsensical. The burden of proof, however, still rests on Hegel to demonstrate that this interpretation is the correct one, that at once all people are “rational”, and that a whole category of people are acting in a way you deem irrational. The steel manned position is that they are functioning in a way which is intelligible, and that you have yet to figure it out. Verily, the case has not been made; the possibility remains that the ritual described is an engagement with the spiritual being &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;behind&lt;/em&gt; the object, and so is an act of communication within an ensouled cosmos as opposed to crude domination. Furthermore, the “higher power” in such systems is often immanent in all things, a pervasive unity of being rather than a separate abstract deity. To accuse such a worldview of a lack of divinity or higher power is to miss a very foundational coherence. A coherence that, ironically, is very Hegelian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While acknowledging intricate political rituals (for example, he mentions the sending of parrot’s eggs in Dahomey as a check on the king), he categorizes all African polities as despotic, held together by external force and the arbitrary will of a ruler. He fails to see the implicit constitutional principles within them. The Ashanti Empire, which he mentions, was a federation held together by a sophisticated constitution named &lt;em&gt;The Great Oath&lt;/em&gt;, a representative council, and legal codes. Defining the State solely in its modern European, bureaucratic incarnation, Hegel in effect renders all preceding political formations, &lt;em&gt;including&lt;/em&gt; those of Ancient Greece or feudal Europe, as preludes. However, he reserves for Africa alone the totalizing verdict of being on the threshold of World History, a present-tense exclusion. There is quite the inconsistency here with respect to Egypt, Chaldea, and India. For Hegel, these represent Spirit’s essential and revered childhood, but he frames their defects, such as the caste system, polytheism (which he accuses Africa of having), or theriomorphic gods, as necessary preludes &lt;em&gt;toward&lt;/em&gt; the Greek and European realization of freedom. &lt;em&gt;They&lt;/em&gt; are on the path, and produced monumental architecture, writing systems, philosophical thought, and so on that European scholarship could recognize as precursors to its own tradition, which it claims is universal. Africa is denied this dignified position as precursor. Its forms of consciousness are not seen as contributing to the dialectic, but as constituting a static ahistorical void beside it. The similarity in stages of consciousness are curious (from a purely structural perspective regarding the relationship between self and world, Africa and this or that cultural sphere might share similarities), alongside the valuation of a diametrically opposed kind. One is a noble beginning, the other is a nullity, a necessary “outside”. While one can argue the bankruptcy of a singular historical dialectic when confronted with the full breadth of human cultural forms, the correct line of argumentation, and what this ultimately proves, is that it is &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; particular narrative. It is not a neutral logical template finding its correlate in the world, but a specific substantive narrative of the ego’s journey to self-conscious freedom as it unfolds in a particular cultural stream. This narrative, which finds its zenith in the modern Germanic-Anglo world and its “consciousness soul”, has no internal place for Africa except as a constitutive outside, a spiritual “state of nature” against which historical consciousness defines itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lesoeuvres.pinaultcollection.com/media/styles/ex_v/s3/art/10487_visuel_REF_MEHRETU_BlackCity.jpg?itok=FXErQ8pO"
loading="lazy"
alt="Black City"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Black City&lt;/em&gt;, Julie Mehretu 2007&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What one can thus accurately term Hegel’s philosophy is not racist in any biological-essentialist sense of a Locke or early Kant. Their racism is additive, being prejudices attached to philosophical systems primarily concerned with other questions (governance and morality, although questions which exclude certain subjects). Hegel’s failing is much wiser. It is “structurally” Eurocentric. His system does not include racist remarks on the basis of biological character, nor does it tie destiny to biology or other such contingencies. Its very architecture, including what results in the trajectory of World-Spirit, identifies the unfolding of self-conscious freedom exclusively with the Greco-Roman to Germanic-Anglo lineage. Structurally, there is a necessary “outside”, or a natural immediate backdrop against which History is defined. His system presents a specific substantive narrative which has no place for Africa, except as an immediacy and externality within the subjecthood of Spirit, resulting from its characteristic mode. Africa becomes this unhistorical ground because of its postulated placement outside state-formation. The Eurocentrism described here is not a moral failing or even a correctable oversight. It is the very expression of the consciousness identified earlier as the systematizing intellect, which seeks to master reality by subsuming it under a single, logical progression. In other words, Europe &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; the center of the world at the time, and in a sense Hegel is &lt;em&gt;rightfully&lt;/em&gt; Eurocentric. His genius was in giving this consciousness the most perfect philosophical form, yet his system’s inability to integrate Africa, except as an excluded void, highlights a limitation. What it does, is describe &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; develops and &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; a thing developed along a certain historical path. But it cannot explain why this development manifested where and when it did, or how other cultural forms relate to it as anything other than precursors, negations, or points along its normative development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Curious, even further, that modernity has “rescued” the status of Africa by claiming that we are all originators from this dark continent. Of course rescued, by providing leader assassinations, IMF and World Bank economic “adjustments”, and resource extraction. Contemporary thought, having internalized this Hegelian marginalization (insofar as Hegel is characteristic of the heights of this epoch’s attempt to make the world intelligible), now attempts a kind of rescue by claiming Africa as the biological cradle of mankind, placing it within “history” using the tools of empirical taxonomy and vague conceptions of society/organization. Yet this “rescue” often replicates the original abstraction: it venerates Africa as an origin point for the &lt;em&gt;species&lt;/em&gt;, while continuing to deny the continent&amp;rsquo;s own historical &lt;em&gt;subjectivity&lt;/em&gt; and political agency. Practices, such as the ones mentioned above, treat the continent as a non-sovereign contributor to the world, as a standing reserve of raw material and testing grounds of modernity’s tools of weaponry, propaganda, financial domination, and so on and so forth. The bankruptcy, is therefore not the single-line historical dialectic, but of the &lt;em&gt;particular&lt;/em&gt; historical content that has been inscribed upon it. This story cannot account for Africa because it was conceived, from the outset, out of its absence. This itself has profound implications, which I will elaborate on in future articles. Ultimately, the ask is not to discard the idea of a spiritual-historical development of man, but to seek a more comprehensive framework, while keeping what works. One which can integrate the rigorous aspects of Hegel’s system, as well as the different, parallel, and specialized spiritual missions of humanity’s various cultural streams. This is the point at which the critique of Hegel necessitates a turn to Rudolf Steiner’s anthroposophy, which posits precisely such a differentiated cosmology of cultural souls and epochs. Steiner offers a model where Europe’s development is one specialized task among many, in a collective human journey, thereby creating a schema where Africa is no longer the constitutive outside, but a vital pole in a manifold spiritual ecology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="anthroposophy"&gt;Anthroposophy
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In order to approach Rudolf Steiner’s Anthroposophy, one must first distinguish it from the theosophical context from which it emerged. While sharing a lexicon (such as “root races, Lemuria [which, if you are familiar with the name, proves my point. It was a name picked up by theosophists, which is why Steiner used the name. It refers to the theory regarding the proposed continent of Lemurs, then was adopted by theosophists to identify the third root race, only to be picked up by Steiner to describe an epochal Earth condition. I personally think it should be called Thermia or Pyria], Atlantis”, etc.), Steiner’s project has differences, some drastic, some minor. Theosophy, as articulated by Blavatsky, often presented racial and cosmological history as a sequential hierarchy of collective spiritual evolution, acting as a map of humanity’s past and future. Steiner, though initially working with this context, broke off from theosophy and began his own movement. For him, these historical and racial differentiations were not ends in themselves, but pedagogical contexts within a larger project devoted to the development of individual spiritual freedom and cognition. In order to do this, he developed a kind of phenomenology of consciousness and freedom to outline a path for the individual “I” to achieve spiritual autonomy. One can read Anthroposophy as a post-Kantian, post-Hegelian endeavor. One which accepts the critique of naive metaphysics and the historical development of spirit, but insists that conscious, methodological inner experience can extend the boundaries of knowledge beyond Hegel’s “Absolute Knowing”, into an active participatory comprehension of the spiritual realities, or the ideal world. His system is less a doctrine, and more a methodological imperative for the evolution of human cognition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steiner’s most challenging, and most relevant, contribution is his model of human difference. To a philosophic audience, his statements on race can be reframed from what appears to be bizarre esotericism, into a historicization of the human form. His proposal is that what we observe empirically as racial differentiation is the surface effect of deeper, epochal shifts in the constitution of human consciousness and its relationship to the spiritual world. The main premise is that human consciousness and its embodied form are not static. They have evolved through distinct, qualitative stages. In earlier stages (which he terms Lemurian, Atlantean), human perception and self-awareness were configured differently. Overall it was, more immersed in spiritual and natural forces, and less individuated. The varying layered constitution of different groups crystallized around these different orientations to spirit and the world. Therefore, “race” is a phenomenon of spiritual history. It is a transient condition of the embodied soul, and a consequence of humanity’s collective spiritual past. This presents a few challenging questions in the face of the framework. For example, if one seeks to transcend race, how can they follow a model which provides such detailed, and &lt;em&gt;often times&lt;/em&gt; hierarchical-sounding descriptions of racial characteristics? Doesn’t this simply create a spiritualized racial essentialism?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is perhaps the most central and valid challenge. A common critique labels Anthroposophy as a form of “spiritualized racial essentialism”. However, the system’s own foundational texts define race in a way that actively dismantles this charge. Race is explicitly termed a transient historical remnant, or a ladder to be used, and then discarded. The core ethical command for the system is the soul’s emancipation from racial peculiarities. Importantly, it institutes an ontological split between the development of the immortal soul and the development of racial forms. To mistake Steiner’s description of these fading forms for a prescription of identity is a misguided reading of a system whose stated goal is to render the very concept of race “meaningless” and form communities based purely on Spirit. In fact, Steiner predicted (it’s not so much a prediction as you could tell this would happen) that the end of isolated tribal lineages and increased “blood mixing” would herald the close of an age where certain forms of instinctive knowledge were tied to “unmixed blood”. This is not only to invoke the kind of miscegenation which conjures to mind modern notions of race (White, Black, Asian), but also to include the kind which has tribes in regional proximity to each other mixing (whether by domination or trade, it does not matter). The loss of these capacities was not a degeneration, it is to be taken as the clearing for the dawn of the rational age. It enables the possibility of a higher, conscious clairvoyance. By nature, this conscious clairvoyance is a spiritual strength achieved based on the individual’s development of the “I”, thus shifting the locus of spiritual power from the physical body (and biological contingency) to the sovereign spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the initial encounter with Steiner’s framework, that is, after the euphoria of finding someone whose project I could get behind, I looked deeper into his comments on race. The fundamental question I wanted to answer, and the question which will also be of importance to differentiating us from previous attempts at “universality”, is how is this different from Hegel’s Eurocentrism? Steiner &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; uses terms like “immediacy”. Hegel places Africa outside history as a state of “immediacy”, yet I critique him, and so isn’t there an inconsistency? The answer I’ve arrived at is that the difference is structural and teleological. Hegel’s judgment is a philosophical verdict within a relatively closed historical dialectic. While he describes a stage, he offers no internal mechanism for Africa to &lt;em&gt;enter&lt;/em&gt; History, except through the formative (and often times colonial) influence of Europe. Steiner is prospective and built on karmic/incarnational fluidity. The “immediacy” or particular spiritual configuration is a starting point for the soul’s journey, and not a final verdict. The individual “I” incarnates into a specific racial/folk context for specific learning, precisely to develop what is lacking. Furthermore, the entire framework is design for its own dissolution. Hegel’s Eurocentrism is a &lt;em&gt;conclusion&lt;/em&gt;. Of course, a critical philosopher must acknowledge the performative contradiction at play. Using the charged language of race in the early 20th century, no matter the intended technical meaning, inevitably invites the opportunity for misinterpretation and misappropriation, no matter how much one clarifies (and Steiner did. Multiple times, he has said that the races he describes in his lectures are not commensurate with the races we find in the world today, and moreover, that we are all essentially the same. The coming of Christ put a formal end to the significance of blood and calls on us to go beyond this contingency). The system’s intent is anti-essentialist, but its historical entanglement with the language of racial science means its effect in the world has the opportunity to reinforce the very patterns it seeks to transcend. Rather than this acting as a refutation of the operative principles at play, it is more so a sober acknowledgement of the space between intent and reception. The goal of reclamation, described earlier, is one way to navigate this space. Surely it is the one which is employed in this article, and one I will continue to explore in future projects. Nevertheless, to fully engage with the critique and assess this space, we must examine Steiner’s &lt;em&gt;specific&lt;/em&gt; characterizations of Africa and the functional role of folk souls within his cosmology. This will help us unveil the principles in his model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Steiner discusses what he terms the “African” soul-mood, or folk soul, his descriptions often center on a preserved relationship to spiritual immediacy and the natural world, words not too dissimilar to Hegel’s. He describes a consciousness less differentiated from the environment, more directly immersed in the rhythms of life and the force of the astral world. While the European “consciousness soul” spearheaded intellectual abstraction and ego-development (a process he described as both necessary and dangerous, I mean just look at the state of Europe and America today), the African cultural sphere retained a connection to a more unified, participatory consciousness. This preserved quality is not a relic in any pejorative sense, but a counter-balancing reservoir for humanity. Its mission is to sustain this connection, providing a spiritual counterweight to European intellectualism and holding a seed of perception that is key for man’s future post-intellectual evolution. This is the mechanism of the folk soul. In Steiner’s system, these are akin to cultural-spiritual ecosystems. Race provides a particular set of conditions, particular challenges, affinities, (a tendency toward intellectual analysis, rhythmic communal life, or maybe a nature-oriented perception). The incarnating individual “I” chooses, based on its karmic needs, to be born into a specific folk soul environment to work with those specific qualities. The folk soul is comparable to a curriculum, where the “I” is a student. The ultimate purpose of this curriculum is for the student to master, and then outgrow it. Therefore, to identify with the folk soul, or to love the transient qualities of one’s race, is to fail the assignment. Success is measured by the ability to lift oneself out of particularities, and integrate their lessons into a liberated individualized spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It must be noted that the cultural epochs named by Steiner are not these rigid historical cages which preclude other cultures and nations from success. We can look to the example of China. Within the anthroposophical framework, China is not assigned a singular, dominant epoch &lt;em&gt;ever&lt;/em&gt;. Yet China is not only a civilization of immense antiquity, and continuity, it is also a decisive global power, which is shaping the material and ideological bounds of this century. What this clarifies for us is that what seems anomalous to the model, does not act as a refutation. China’s trajectory demonstrates that the spiritual mission of a cultural sphere is to develop its own distinctive qualities, whether in statecraft or philosophy, across vast stretches of time. Its current rise highlights Steiner’s point, that epochs describe specialized developmental tasks and modes of consciousness. That an epoch is named for a culture only describes where this tendency most prominently emerges. Any idea which conceives of the cultural epochs as a “ruling of the world” is misguided, as is the conception of these cultural epochs as placing certain cultures and civilizations in the “dominator” role. History is, after all, a manifold of parallel and interacting spiritual phenomena, each with its own contribution to the whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The doctrines of reincarnation and karma are what change Steiner’s historic model into a pedagogy for the soul. Where Hegel’s totality unfolds through nations and states across world history, a part of Steiner’s totality, is the journey of the “I” across soul history through successive incarnations. Reincarnation ensures that the folk context one is born into is a “classroom” of sorts. A soul incarnates into a specific racial-folk environment (or classroom) by karmic necessity to balance experiences, or develop lacking faculties and the like. What this means is that the spiritual characteristics Steiner associates with a group are not essential traits binding its members, but are more comparable to a palette of potential lessons available to any soul that enters that environment for a time. What Hegel could only see as a fixed “stage” of World-Spirit becomes, in Steiner’s system, a recurrent experiential modality within the infinite curriculum of individual spiritual development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: I am taking it as given the existence of reincarnation as a phenomenon, for the purposes of engaging with Steiner’s system. However, for those who remain unconvinced, it is worth nothing that this is not an arbitrary assertion. Serious empirical research into the phenomenon, most notably the decades of cross-cultural case studied compiled by psychiatrists like Ian Stevenson, or even the &lt;a class="link" href="https://med.virginia.edu/perceptual-studies/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;University of Virginia’s Division of Perceptual Studies&lt;/a&gt;, provides a body of anomalous data. This includes children with detailed, verifiable memories of previous lives, which challenges strict materialist/physicalist paradigms. This research does not “prove” Steiner’s cosmology, surely. After all, it could be the case that a subject is tapping into some collective bank of experiences and not in reality being that person, however, is this itself not a kind of reincarnation? What this literature certainly does establish is that the concept of reincarnation is not merely a poetic flourish. It is a genuine hypothesis with empirical backing. The framework of Anthroposophy offers one coherent way to make sense of such data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a clear relationship between the “I” and the temporary racial condition. Race is ultimately instrumental and temporary, and the “I” uses the racial-folk context as a learning apparatus. Let us give a concrete example of this framework. The Black American struggle, culminating in movements led by figures like Dr. Martin Luther King Jr., can be seen a collective enactment of this anthroposophical principle. Here was a people whose racial designation was used to construct a brutally limiting environment of subjugation and exclusion. Their spiritual and political achievement did not find them identifying with this imposed racial identity, opting instead to master its most painful lessons and then transcend it. By invoking the universal ideals of personhood, equality, and inalienable rights, which were principles embedded in the very constitutional fabric of the nation that excluded them, they did not end up becoming “white” or European. They instead compelled America to recognize a failed universality it had professed but failed to embody. The “hierarchy” of race was invalidated and thereby ushered in a more universal standard of citizenship for all, effectively lifting the whole society out of the particularities of race each person finds themselves in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leads to the clarification that within Steiner’s system, to be born into a racial or folk category predicts nothing essential about the individual’s spiritual constitution, capacity, or destiny. The individual ultimately has their own developmental agenda. One soul may incarnate into a specific racial context to develop patience through oppression. Another may incarnate there to develop the strength to lead a struggle for justice, and yet another may be there to cultivate artistic expression from within a particular rhythmic tradition (hence the common adage of white musicians being met with “he must have been black in a past life”). No racial category carries a deterministic spiritual signature for the individual, and more than that, there is no significant spiritual content within “race”. The characteristics Steiner describes are tendencies of the environment, which follows that the “African” soul-mood of immediacy or “European” drive for abstraction are spiritual climates. But within each climate exists every conceivable type of seeker, thinker, and pioneer. The ultimate freedom of the “I” is proven in its very capacity to manifest in ways that defy any and all collective typologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“In our age, primary attention should not be paid to racial descent but rather to the living impulse expressed in the words of St. Paul: Not I, but Christ in me.”&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;— Rudolf Steiner, 1911-03-07 GA124&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="reclamation"&gt;Reclamation
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The preceding analysis leaves us at an impasse. The tensions within German Idealism and Anthroposophy, having traced their grand, universalizing architectures, have been laid out and confronted. The Afro-Pessimist challenge in this context draws an illogical conclusion. Discard the tools, for they were forged for your exclusion. Yet the different, more demanding, path has presented itself. If the works of past contributors to human knowledge can be compared to ovals, and we seek &lt;em&gt;the wheel&lt;/em&gt;, then the task is not to reject the oval and attempt to invent the wheel anew from scratch (ending in futility). No, it is to see the flattened sides of Eurocentrism and the non-uniformity of racial hierarchy as constituting our given material (holding onto the oval metaphor), and using the principles of geometric reasoning inherent to its creation, work it into a true circle. This is immanent critique, the application of a system’s own highest standards and rigor to correct its flaws, internal contradictions, and appraise the system as being worthy or not of reclamation. Hegel’s commentary on Africa (not touching on India, China, his thoughts on music, etc.) represents a kind of contingency which denies subjectivity and due process to Africa at worst, and completely mischaracterizes it at best. However, we’ve arrived at this conclusion using the standards present in his system itself and &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; via a moralizing critique or external standard, this being the demand for a concrete universality that can account for all of human being. The structure itself has an unrealized potentiality, demanding that its claims of universality be made genuinely universal. Steiner has informed us that there is an imperative in spiritual emancipation, such that it clarifies that racial descriptions must be read as fading diagnostics and not eternal truths, certainly not the kind which makes the individual unfree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such projects are often met with skepticism. Why labor within frameworks that are supposedly scarred by the pathologies of their age? The answer is quite simple. A truly innovative thought or creation, whether it be the Categorical Imperative, the Speculative Method, or the concept of Freedom, does not remain the property of its originator, nor was it ever “theirs” in the first place. If it is genuine, it becomes part of the commonwealth of human consciousness. And nor is the genesis solely in the individual. When one finds that they are inspired, they truly are in-spirited. They have an insight from another awaken and resonate within their own capacity for reason and spirit. In that very moment, the innovation ceases to be theirs and becomes a living tool for creation. Likewise, as a thinker shaped by the West and standing in critical relation to its failures, I do not engage as an outsider. I engage as a participant of its continuum, claiming the right to separate the method from the madness. Likewise, each new world historical “innovation” of a culture becomes the new standard of the world, and the world must adjust. Modernity, did not merely &lt;em&gt;offer&lt;/em&gt; innovations, it established the new global standard by which all other societies would be compelled to measure and recognize themselves. The innovations it provides, such as the capitalist nation-state and the ideology of the sovereign individual, coalesced into a totalizing system. This system was then universalized by competitive necessity and of course colonial imposition. The world was re-made in modernity’s image, rendering all alternatives of being either assimilated, marginalized, or rendered historical. When a new world historical innovation appears on the stage, it will also alter the world, whether it be a change in consciousness, or a new technological paradigm (which will fundamentally alter our being such that it can be described as a change in consciousness. Take that how you will.).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The definitive proof that this reclamation is neither naive nor futile is in the history I’ve mentioned before: the Haitian revolution. The enslaved Africans of Saint-Domingue didn’t petition for entry into a French universalism that hypocritically excluded them. What they did was seize the universal principle of liberty itself, and through their struggle, compelled the world to witness its instantiation. Was this a “European” tool they used? Or was it an exposure of the European failure to grasp their own tools&amp;rsquo; logic? Haiti demonstrated that the most potent critique of a flawed universal is in its very enactment. In the same spirit, the work of immanent critique today is to take the various “ovals” of philosophies and frameworks and, through the application of their own very standards, work them into the circles they should be, rather than re-inventing the wheel. In spite of this, an apparent final philosophical test is yet to be faced. It is in the face of the claims of Afro-Pessimism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-challenge-of-afro-pessimism"&gt;The &amp;ldquo;challenge&amp;rdquo; of Afro-pessimism
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/2/26/Slave-ship.jpg"
loading="lazy"
alt="AP"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Slave Ship&lt;/em&gt;, by J. M. W. Turner, 1840&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Afro-pessimist position, mentioned earlier as being articulated by Frank B. Wilderson III, stands as more than a critique of racism or exclusion. It is a political doctrine that states that Blackness is constituted as the logical negation upon which the very category of Human, and subsequently Social life, is built. Blackness is not an identity among others that has been excluded from a pre-existing humanity, but is rather the constitutive outside against which humanity defines itself. The slave represents the ontological anti-thesis to personhood insofar as, following along the logic of modernity, they are mere objects in a position of social death, as opposed to laborers. “Social death” here, implies a position of &lt;em&gt;ontological&lt;/em&gt; exclusion from the bounds of personhood and relations that define social life. From this perspective, the “entanglements” traced in Kant, Hegel, and Locke are logical necessities of a world structured by this anti-Black antagonism. The universalism proposed by such thinkers are not unfinished, they are in actuality finished closed circuits from which their very coherence depends on the barring of Blackness. Immanent critique would be diagnosed as a category error, or mistake which has a logically impossible end. If the Afro-pessimist is correct, the not only is the endeavor of “not re-inventing the wheel” and reclamation difficult, it is futile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To this challenge, one must begin with a concession. Afro-pessimism &lt;em&gt;rightfully&lt;/em&gt; describes the historical record and the failed instantiations of these philosophies. It provides the most cogent explanation for why the Enlightenment’s “Rights of Man” could coexist with the Middle Passage, or why Hegel’s World-Spirit could consign Africa to an ahistorical void, and why any universalism birthed within the context of the Trans-Atlantic Slave Trade (hereby referred to as TAST) carries the scent of death. Individuals such as Domenico Losurdo might have previously documented the savage dialectic of modernity, particularly of the Liberal paradigm and its grim underbelly. For example, it may seem paradoxical that alongside liberalism, you find the very illiberal policies of slavery, colonialism, genocide, racism, and so on and so forth. But AP takes this insight and recognizes it as an ontological principle at work. This principle is claimed to be that the concept of the modern human is born from the historical negation of the Black.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the more perceptive among you might have noticed that I have avoided defining race in this article. This is another thing which Afro-pessimists are insightful on, the historical formation of the concept. The TAST was what &lt;em&gt;created&lt;/em&gt; what we now understand as blackness, particularly as a category of what they claim is social death, as the foundational negativity of modern political ontology. The economic system of the modern age required a new pseudo-scientific (with the aims of justifying itself institutionally) taxonomy of human value. Thus, race becomes a category in the grand systematizing project of the Germanic-Anglo epoch, as an expression of its abstracting, quantifying consciousness. A brief genealogy of justification will show that the concept has always been philosophically unstable. Its justifications began with empirical taxonomy, retreating into metaphysical genetics (any grouping of what makes a race &lt;em&gt;a race&lt;/em&gt; becomes “begging the question”), and now it has circled back to a crude, pre-critical apprehension in the form of “just look, people are different!”. From its inception, race has been a problem of category error, chasing a material basis that it can never truly find. In essence, race can be defined as a deliberate confusion of categories born from the TAST. This must be distinguished from ethnicity, which is a perennial human reality (although just as historically contingent. specific ethnicities have not always existed). Where ethnicity concerns lineage and culture, race is a modern sign that appeals primarily to the epidermal character of man within a socially determined reality. This distinction is important since it allows us to recognize the Black American ethnicity, which is a real historically forged cultural identity with its own traditions, struggles, and ethnogenesis, as a creation &lt;em&gt;born from&lt;/em&gt; the imposed racial category of Black &lt;em&gt;in America&lt;/em&gt;, without conflating the two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above are indispensable parts of AP’s claim. However, AP runs into a very big contradiction almost immediately. In its totalizing diagnostic rigor, it inadvertently replicates the very metaphysical closure it ascribes to modernity. It correctly identifies how modernity constructs the Human through the negation of the Black, defining blackness as a position of social death. But it performs a self-negation. It deprives the Black of historical subjectivity and potentiality. AP freezes the Black in the position of the object, the constituted outside, and in doing so, denying the very possibility of a conduct that is not always-already captured by the “grammar” of slavery. The very lack of a normative project is itself telling, insofar as for thinkers like Locke, their conclusion that blacks are inferior is a result of modernity. The very same can be said about AP as a modern verdict that mirrors the kind of closure it supposedly critiques. This“freezing” is especially evident in its engagement with Frantz Fanon. The notion of “ontological non-being” was extracted from Fanon’s work &lt;em&gt;Black Skin, White Masks&lt;/em&gt; by AP. The “zone of non-being” mentioned in the text is a lived negation to be worked through, resulting in the creation of a new humanism. AP’s reading freezes this moment into a permanent condition, disabling the Black subject. Compare this to the figure of Malcolm X, who exposes this rejection. He began with the same negativity. With the erasure of the slave name and the replacement of it with “X”, marking a new, open subjectivity, he was under no pretenses that he was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; constituted, in part, by a slave system. However, he used that negativity as the beginning of a new universality, moving from Black nationalism towards a broader human solidarity found in Islam. AP, in contrast, seems perpetually stuck at the moment of recognition, wallowing in this moment, seemingly inept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While one may accuse me of ad hominem, the question raised by the life choices of theorists like Frank Wilderson points to a genuine tension in the unity of thought and being. If the anti-black world is truly total, and all cross-racial relations are corrupted by the grammar of slavery, what is the status of Wilderson’s own life and relationships? He is, after all, married to a white woman, and operates within the very “white” field of academia. In the end, AP’s greatest strength in its unflinching description of the anti-blackness found within modernity becomes its weakness. Elevating social death from a historical condition to an ontological fate builds a cage around the subject, denying them the tools of their own liberation, and in the end, in hopes of being a theory in the name of describing impossibility, ends up canonizing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, my critique echoes Jean Baudrillard’s diagnosis of the postmodern condition. He argues that the masses respond to the overproduction of social and political meaning with a silent majoritarian strategy of absorption and neutralization. A kind of passive resistance that implodes meaning. Similarly, one might argue that AP, in its totalizing negativity, performs a theoretical hyperreality. Mapping the grammar of slavery with such exhaustive precision, its profound description of social death becomes a &lt;em&gt;simulation&lt;/em&gt; of that death, or in other words, a closed intellectual system where all potential resistance, or normativity, is pre-emptively nullified as either naive or complicit. Like Baudrillard’s silent majorities absorbing and deflecting all messages, the AP framework can absorb all historical instances of black agency such as Haiti, the Civil Rights Movement, and Malcolm X as mere epiphenomena within the unchanging structure, thereby neutralizing their significance. Put this way, AP does not merely describe a condition of impossibility, it performs a simulation of that impossibility, mirroring the very absorptive, negating logic of the modernity which it critiques. It’s a very poignant form of theoretical surrender. The depth of the analysis is mistaken for the finality of the verdict.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://smarthistory.org/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/compared.jpg"
loading="lazy"
alt="Napoleon"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Napoleon Leading the Army over the Alps&lt;/em&gt;, Kehinde Wiley 2005&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, we should return to the initial question: how can we value philosophical systems built to be exclusionary? We have examined the architectures of Kant, Hegel, and Steiner in an effort to explore their claims and discover what is to be valued. The AP response is to declare these systems irredeemably corrupt, saying “we &lt;em&gt;can’t&lt;/em&gt; value them”. Declaring the very tools of universal reason to be poisoned at the source by the ontological crime of the TAST, it renders reclamation of such projects worse than naive- it’s a psychological coping mechanism for those unable to face the void. I have argued that such a conclusion, for all its rhetorical force (perhaps forceful to a pessimist, maybe), is itself a profound error. It is a theoretical dead end that, in the name of critique, delivers an addictive reliance to the very totality it claims to describe. Against this closed circuit of impossibility, the open-ended work of immanent critique must be posed, finding its most far-reaching expression in the often-misunderstood system of Rudolf Steiner. While Kant and Hegel may provide initial frameworks, it is in Anthroposophy that we find a metaphysical architecture explicitly designed for the task of transcending contingencies. Anthroposophy does not shy away from the historical reality of “racial” differentiations, whether born from the TAST-era consciousness, or from before then. The ultimate goal is to dissolve transient qualities and create community based on individual spiritual maturity. This approach provides the tools to actively overcome essentialisms and exclusionary frameworks in the development of one’s own being. Therefore, the solution to the problem of exclusion is not to be found in AP’s passive cage. It is in the active, disciplined labor of working with what you have, in order to build what should be.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Unintelligibility of Intelligence and IQ</title><link>https://goddesscameo.github.io/p/the-unintelligibility-of-intelligence-and-iq/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://goddesscameo.github.io/p/the-unintelligibility-of-intelligence-and-iq/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://cdn.thecollector.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/thinker-auguste-rodin-what-so-special.jpg" alt="Featured image of post The Unintelligibility of Intelligence and IQ" /&gt;&lt;h2 id="what-is-intelligence"&gt;What is intelligence?
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some people have it, some think they have it, some want it, and some think they want it. Intelligence is one of those things we claim to recognize but struggle to define. At times, we point to a clever solution, or an ingenious insight and say “&lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; is intelligent”, yet when we try to pin down the essence of what we’re pointing at, the concept fragments. In the modern paradigm, intelligence serves at once as a stand for three different things: an action, a metric, and a vague idea of inherent cognitive worth. Rather than being incidental, this is precisely the root of the problem. The cart has been placed before the horse. Employing a precise &lt;em&gt;looking&lt;/em&gt; metric - the IQ test - to quantify a concept that has never been coherently defined, we use the resulting numbers to retroactively justify the very definition we presume to measure. As a result, this circular logic has trapped us in a paradigm where we measure what we can, rather than seeking to understand what &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://i.imgur.com/bbJG7n3.png"
loading="lazy"
alt="Inter"
&gt;&lt;img src="https://i.imgur.com/aOBFsag.png"
loading="lazy"
alt="Leg"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To break this cycle, we need to return to the source, and the key lies in the word itself, particularly in its etymology. &lt;em&gt;Intelligence&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;intelligible&lt;/em&gt; share the Latin root &lt;em&gt;intelligere&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;em&gt;inter&lt;/em&gt; (between) and &lt;em&gt;legere&lt;/em&gt; (to gather, to choose, to read). This etymology unveils intelligence not as a static possession, but as active relationship; the etymology reveals intelligence as the active capacity “to read between”, to discern patterns and meaning, thereby rendering the world intelligible. Intelligence is therefore a relational event that unfolds in the relationship between the subject and the world. To be intelligent is to engage in the perpetual act of interpretation, of translating patterns, symbols, and structures of reality, into a coherent meaning. The world itself is a kind of text, rich with potential intelligibility, and with mind as its reader. The two exist in a co-creative polarity: an intelligible world invites reading, and an intelligent mind searches for something to read. An intelligent being is one that can make sense of its context, and an intelligent world is one that can be meaningfully read. They are two sides of the same coin. This dynamic dismantles a dominant trend we’ll call the “banking” model of knowledge, where a conflation between information storage and comprehension is made. Surely the storage of information allows one to fashion from it understandings and readings, but the mere fact of acquiring factoids alone does not constitute an intelligent person. In addition to this trend, another trend is dismantled, one we’ll be calling the “processor” model, which conflates “computational speed” with genuine insight. True intelligence is not measured by what one &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt;, but by the depth and relevance of the connections formed in dialogue with reality. This relational view even carries a moral/normative dimension. The highest intelligence becomes a form of literacy, a capacity to read a forest as an ecosystem or living domain, a person as a history or living thing with a past and a future. The intelligent person is engaged in the ongoing project of rendering the world meaningful, and in doing so, participating in the very unfolding of its intelligibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This perspective also reveals that intelligence is not the sole province of the conscious human mind. An object within a coherent system possesses a kind of contextual intelligence. Its very form and function “read” and answer the demands of the system (or mind) it helps constitute, rendering this mind stable, operational, and of course, intelligible. A perfect geometric crystal is an implicit argument of natural law. Its facets express, with an almost perfect logic, the mathematical constraints of molecular forces and symmetry, unified in the higher ideality of its intelligibility. The deepest form of intelligibility, or intelligence, is here a sense in which an object, or perhaps even a logic or pattern, which belongs “natively” (or rather colloquially) to a different system altogether, existing in the fabric of another. True intelligence, as the capacity to “read between”, excels at this cross-contextual mapping (and here I am to make a case for a resurgence in renaissance men and generalist education, but let’s stay on topic). Consider a very compelling example which came to me many years ago: take the case of a virologist who becomes an exceptional social media manager. Their expertise is not in memes, but in the underlying dynamics of virality. The conditions of a host environment, the thresholds of contagion, perhaps even the mutation of a message (which &lt;em&gt;translates&lt;/em&gt; to memetics), in addition to an intuitive understanding of pathways of transmission are what they are educated in. They possess a profound literacy in one system (biological contagion), whose abstract relational logic is isomorphic to another (informational contagion). As such, their intelligence is not demonstrated by storing facts about “trending topics” or “viruses”, but by successfully grasping the deeper intelligibility which interacts with and governs both domains. In this sense, the phrase “going viral” in the context of the virtual world has &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; more in common with the natural world than it may seem. This is the hallmark of true intelligence, grasping the intelligible form of a process so clearly that its echo can be discerned in a seemingly foreign territory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The object itself is the solution to a problem, it is an intelligent object that makes the invisible structure/relationality of its context legible. If one would like to interpret the previous sentence another way, the heuristic in systems thinking: &lt;a class="link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_purpose_of_a_system_is_what_it_does" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;the purpose of a system is what it does&lt;/a&gt; can serve us well. The object is in a dialogue with the whole. Life itself is this principle incarnate and active. A growing root navigates soil not by calculating as if it had the same kind of mind we do, but by being-there in a living dialogue with the whole of nature and with the whole of itself. Encountering gravity, moisture, obstacles, temperature, and more, it successfully reads between these variables of its environment to solve the problem of survival. An ecosystem self-regulates, and within this system, its species and processes are locked in a dance of change. Biological life cannot possibly be a passenger in an intelligible universe. It is itself a creative form of that universe’s fundamental intelligibility as a continuous morphing act of interpretation and response that perpetuates the very conditions for being read. This chain of intelligibility implies a culminating coherence: the most complete, self-sufficient, and all-encompassing “mind” or system, which philosophy and theology would term the Absolute, or God. By this same logic, this would be the ultimate intelligibility. It would be that in which all partial contexts find their final reference, the absolute source of pattern and meaning in which every subsidiary “reading”, from the smallest particle to the highest angels, coheres, and is perfectly rendered intelligible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us return from the heights of this overview and demonstrate a more practical scenario. This model also clarifies a common paradox we find today: The person hailed as “smart” who fails to live up to their potential. This designation isn’t based on an abstract hidden quality, it is a verdict based on &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; prior demonstration of a moment where they successfully produced an insight or created something. In other words, the only reason they are said to be intelligent is because they have showed it in the past, and the only reason they aren’t at this moment, is because of some disconnect between them and the world. Their very capacity created the expectation. Subsequent failure wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be a mismeasurement of some internal asset, failure is what results from a breakdown in their ongoing relationship with the world. Perhaps a person is going through a depressing period in thier life, perhaps they lack confidence for this or that reason. Nonetheless, what this situation highlights is a moment of dialectic which constitutes intelligence/intelligibility. It requires both the capacity to discern, and the &lt;em&gt;concrete will&lt;/em&gt; to engage. To call someone intelligent is to recognize a pattern of successful past readings; to say they are wasting their intelligence is to observe a present refusal to enter into &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; meaningful dialogue. Thus, potential cannot be a ghost in the machine. Potential, in the context of man, is the unfulfilled promise of the relationship between a particular mind and the world it is capable of reading. The person and their potential are not separate, they are two descriptions of the same relational capacity, seen from the vantage point of past manifestation and future possibility. Truly, it is wasted potential for someone who has the capacity to be in the world and contribute to its intelligibility be plagued by either conditions outside themselves, or by internal ailments needed to be worked through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not a surprise, then, that those who brandish the highest IQ scores are rarely the ones who change the world. Consider MENSA, a group defined by this exclusive metric. Its members collectively have not produced the defining innovations, art, or social transformations neither of our age, nor historically which have defined Western civilization. The common retort in defense of this metric is that world-changers like Einstein (I will grant that he has changed the paradigm of physics with GR and SR, not that is true) &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; had high IQs, is a sleight of hand. It mistakes an occasional correlation for a causal necessity, while ignoring the vast majority of high-IQ individuals who produce nothing of comparable significance. This defense commits a few errors we will fully expand on later, but of which we can get a rough idea of here. Firstly, a conflation between the narrow skill of test-taking abstraction with the generative capacity and action that remakes and co-participates in reality. Secondly, it overlooks the essential non-IQ factors such as perseverance, moral vision, and the capacity to &lt;em&gt;find&lt;/em&gt; problems rather than solving pre-framed ones. Third, it cherry-picks historical geniuses post-hoc, using their legendary status to validate the metric rather than questioning why the metric fails to predict such genius in the living. This is not to say high scorers are devoid of talent, only that test scores capture a shadow of what’s required to really “read between” the lines of reality and “write a new chapter”, so to say. I suppose this clarification protects against the straw manned response of saying “Iapetus thinks someone with an IQ of 60 can change the world”. No, I want to problematize everything about this modern approach, including the biology-mind/IQ connection. Have you, for example, heard of the &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.cbc.ca/radio/asithappens/as-it-happens-thursday-edition-1.3679117/scientists-research-man-missing-90-of-his-brain-who-leads-a-normal-life-1.3679125" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;French man missing 90% of his brain&lt;/a&gt;, and despite that having an IQ of 84 and living a relatively normal life? The world is bigger than it seems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cross-contextual mapping of this kind points towards the idea that intelligence is not a bundle of separate, domain-specific modules, but a unitary core faculty. It is one unified foundational capacity for relationship discernment, and yes, problem-solving. What varies is not the &lt;em&gt;kind&lt;/em&gt; of intelligence, but the medium and level it works at. Given that this unified capacity involves the discernment of patterns of relationship, the artist and the scientist, the poet and the philosopher, ultimately perceive the same intelligible pattern in the world, but one renders it as metaphor and &lt;em&gt;work&lt;/em&gt; which stirs the soul, while the other translates it into an equation or logical explication, which just as much may stir the soul, but nonetheless is conveyed differently than the former two. Moreso, the very reason our very “reading the world” transforms from age to age is not accidental. It follows from a necessary evolution in the way we make intelligibility intelligible to us in the first place. For if meaning was fully available in its conveyance at the point of contact, it would imply we have a proximity to the divine mind of God that goes in contrast to everything we know and can know at this point in time. It would be a totalizing knowledge entirely alien to the human condition. Instead, we don’t encounter the “whole” truth, we approach it through a succession of partial evolving perspectives, which themselves have a telos (which I will not cover in this essay). The intelligence, or intelligibility, of millennia past is in continuity with the one today. Each stage in how we make the world intelligible is therefore a corrective to the limitations of the last, and a step in the long awakening of the mind to its own implicit potential and to the realities it seeks to know.
We think we know what intelligence is. We measure it in numbers, rank it in percentiles, use it to categorize people, and sort or determine the worth of children and adults. What if the most “intelligent” thing you could do today is to recognize that everything we &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; we know about intelligence is misguided and, in some cases, harmful? What if the modern concept is not only flawed, not only a category error, but misconceived entirely and disconnected from the culmination of it prior to its current ~500 year long iteration? As you continue, this essay demonstrates that the fragmented phantom of intelligence we have today, is inadequate. Additionally, it demonstrates that there is necessity in tracing its disappearance from the universe, into the skull, and onto a Scantron sheet, in order to place it back where it ought to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-history-of-consciousness"&gt;The History of Consciousness
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;If intelligence is the act of “reading between” the self and the world, then the question which guides our investigation is: “Where does this intelligibility come from”? For us modern men (and women), the answer is passive, mechanical nature. The “reading” is a private activity of our individual brains. However, this is a recent, and might I add, very impoverished answer. To grasp the full depth of our definition, we must recognize that intelligence and consciousness are two facets of the same event. Consciousness (from &lt;em&gt;con&lt;/em&gt; [with] + and &lt;em&gt;scire&lt;/em&gt; [to know]) is, simply put, our state of &lt;em&gt;being with&lt;/em&gt; knowledge, the condition of a being capable of rendering its world intelligible. Therefore, the history of consciousness is the history of intelligibility itself. Not the intelligibility of things per se, but intelligibility in general. In effect, it is the history of the evolving method of that rendering. Each cultural age represents a distinct schooling of the human spirit in a specific mode of “reading”. In the not-too-distant past, one would not say “&lt;em&gt;I think&lt;/em&gt;”, but “&lt;em&gt;it thinks in me&lt;/em&gt;”. This is since each mode is indicative of a different order of intelligibility than another. Likewise, our current “stage” or mode of consciousness differs from the last. In order to understand our current paradigm, we must journey to a time when the source of intelligibility was not found in the skull, but experienced in the world as a revelation from a living totality/universe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: Jean Gebser’s terminology will be used here and there in addition to Steiner’s terminology in order to describe the structural stages that characterize the relationship between intelligibility and consciousness. There is great overlap between what they describe, however they are different projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="indian"&gt;Indian
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Before the &lt;em&gt;soul&lt;/em&gt; of man could make what it saw before it intelligible, the human soul needed to clarify the “that” of what it was making intelligible in the first place. The faculty necessary for the &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt;-ness of intelligibility is the very capability to recognize that there is something meaningful to be grasped. It was the Indian cultural age which provided this certainty through an inward spiritual memory. It established the foundation that &lt;em&gt;being&lt;/em&gt; is spiritual in essence. Without this anchor, all subsequent exploration risks concluding that the material world is the only reality. The Vedanta and Upanishads are fundamentally concerned with transcending the material world (Maya) and realizing the ultimate spiritual unity (Brahman), or ideal/total unity for you Hegelheads, through the inward turning and contemplation of knowledge (Jnana). The famous dictum &lt;em&gt;Tat Tvam Asi&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;Thou art That&lt;/em&gt;, captures this age’s focus. The individual soul is not to understand the world, but to continuously remember and establish its identity with the universal “source”. Intelligibility/intelligence here is the intuitive recognition of a pre-existing, all-encompassing spiritual, or ideal, whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, the first attitude of intelligibility is one of undifferentiated unity. Gebser would term this the archaic structure, where consciousness is an undeveloped embedding in the world. Consciousness here has not yet become self-reflective, it lies in an immersive state where inner “thought”, and outer “being”, or event, are indistinguishable. Meaning isn’t deciphered, there isn’t room for a stage of explicit recursion. Instead, there is a conscious anchoring in undifferentiated spiritual unity, which provides the necessary ground for all subsequent development. Without this anchor, man’s turn toward the world risks complete disorientation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="persian"&gt;Persian
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stages of positivity always necessarily invite negation. What this means for consciousness, after establishing the positive unity of self and world, is that it must learn discernment. Zoroastrianism presents the cosmos as a grand battle between the spirit of light, truth, and order (Ahura Mazda), and the spirit of darkness, falsehood, and chaos (Angra Mainyu, or Ahriman. We will see him return later). Man here has a moral, or normative, duty to cultivate &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; creation (such as agriculture and truth-telling) and fight against corruption. An active will-centric engagement finds intelligibility discerning between good and bad in every aspect of life, and as a result, choosing sides. At this stage, existence itself is unified with morality, or normativity, from the perspective of consciousness. The notion that &amp;ldquo;being is good&amp;rdquo; can be found in various proofs today, but for it to be intelligible to man, it was first established concretely here. In Gebser’s terms, we would see the magical structure as dominant. We find that consciousness is enacted through ritual, rhythm, and eventually, a &lt;em&gt;magical&lt;/em&gt; empathy with natural forces. Magical is the correct word here, since magic is the immediate attempt of subjectivity to control nature directly, without mediation by an objective universality. The archaic is a zero-point of “embedding”, while the magical, is marked by point-like, group-oriented awareness and a fluid, pre-perspectival sense of space and causality. This magical event characterizes the moment of pre-conscious differentiation, before consciousness awakes to narrative/myth in the next section. Steiner would correctly see this as the moment of dream-like instinctive clairvoyance (which has a technical definition in his system, although it is related to the everyday understanding) where the human being lived in an unconscious unity with cosmic beings, forces, and idealities. Both would agree that this stage is indicative of a profound connection, or unity, yet lacks individual freedom and the capacity for critical thought and critical self-awareness (which, of course, is implied by differentiation).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To better grasp the distinction between the archaic and the magical, the Aboriginal concept of &lt;em&gt;Dreamtime&lt;/em&gt;, has a direct correlate here, and is also reflective of Steiner’s descriptions of pre-historic consciousness. The individual and group are not yet fully distinct, and the human and natural worlds are bound in a web of participation. In Dreamtime, the Ancestor Beings, the land, the people, etc. are all part of a single continuous being. A person is not just &lt;em&gt;on&lt;/em&gt; the land, they are a particular &lt;em&gt;part&lt;/em&gt; of it, descended from, and in continuity with, the Ancestor who formed it. This description is a quintessential example of the magical-participatory relationship. Time is fluid, it lacks linear sequentiality, and so Dreamtime is not “a long, long time ago”, it is the eternal &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;everywhen&lt;/em&gt;. Ritualistic actions as a result are not commemorative events, they are actions which invoke a participation and re-actualization of the ongoing creative power of Dreamtime (and thus, like the moral dimension of the Zoroastrian belief, there is a moral imperative here of maintenance to the land), or of intelligibility and intelligence. However, it is also worth noting that there is some overlap with the next stage we will discuss, the mythic structure. Because the Dreamtime involves narrative and has this image-based quality, which is a hallmark of the mythic structure, it can be said to be a &lt;em&gt;preserved&lt;/em&gt; form of what Steiner calls “old Imaginative consciousness”, or instinctive clairvoyance. The good news is that this reveals that these structures are not rigid boxes, but interpenetrating states of being. Dreamtime stands as a testament to this fluidity, and so is not the “primitive” form of the later mythic structure. The core of consciousness remains magical, while its expression takes on a narrative image-based form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="egyptian-chaldean"&gt;Egyptian-Chaldean
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The mythic structure is the stage where consciousness, intelligibility, intelligence, however you want to call it, awakens to polarity and rhythm. It expresses itself in symbols and images, or narratives/myths (hence mythic structure). The world is perceived as a drama of spiritual beings/idealities and forces. The participatory engagement of the Magical structure is crystallized. So it follows that the diffuse forces found in Persia coalesce into the images, symbols, and myths of Gods. Intelligibility is a matter of participating in a struggle here no longer, it is now concerned with decoding the divine language written into the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note on myth&lt;/strong&gt;: mythology often times has this colloquially implied meaning of “created” or fictional, but an etymological review of the word reveals mythology as &lt;em&gt;the study of what was uttered/spoken&lt;/em&gt;. The modern implication that these narratives and stories are all misguided, that, because they didn’t have the scientific tools we do now, they didn’t have the &lt;em&gt;truth&lt;/em&gt;, assumes our ancestors were incompetent versions of ourselves, stumbling and bumbling towards a truth only we possess. For if they were so incompetent, the possibility of generating &amp;ldquo;superior&amp;rdquo; beings such as us surely wouldn&amp;rsquo;t come to be. The steel-manned position of ancient attitudes would view them &lt;em&gt;at the very minimum&lt;/em&gt; as working with what they had at the time. It would see that myth and stories are not a failed attempt at our kind of fact, but a sophisticated vehicle of a different order. In order to convey important information (such as regarding the human condition, the universe, the moral order, or the great chain of being), a medium and method that does not risk the integrity of that message is needed which accomplishes these things. The ancients developed a peerless method here. Thus, the story and symbol serves as the perfect vehicle to convey such information. Statues, carvings, stories, and so on have the express purpose of preserving and imparting wisdom. The refusal to engage with this reality and reduce it to primitive fiction is not a sign of sophistication. Quite the opposite, actually. It describes a very specific kind of poverty in our own current mode of understanding, which is an attitude we will address later on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Egyptians and Chaldeans perfected this “reading”. The movements of the stars in Babylonian astrology (which also deserves a standalone article) do not exist as flat astronomical data. They, instead, reveal the will of the universe in narrative form. For example, the journey of Ra, or the drama of Osiris’s death and re-birth are not natural events we look to and find in the natural world using our mode of consciousness. They’re chapters in a sacred story where time is cyclical, among other things. Intelligibility is required to learn this “symbolic script”, a task for the astronomer, priest, or the initiated. This here is a historical demonstration of Steiner’s “imaginative consciousness”. Consciousness awakens to polarity and rhythm and perceives the drama of the world. The self, in the face of this drama, becomes a receiver and interpreter of these revelations, and moves beyond the “magical participation”, found in the previous age, towards a structured understanding of the world/universe, but still in an age within the paradigm where the source of meaning is external as a result of the early differentiation from unity. The source of intelligibility remains “out there” in the utterances of the gods, but the mind now actively engages in the work of its translation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="greco-roman"&gt;Greco-Roman
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fundamental shift from the “mythic” structure into the next (called the mental structure) is characterized best by the Greeks. Intelligence becomes redefined from a faculty of participation by interpreting the acts of external divine intelligence/intelligibility, to being the faculty of an individual subject which generates comprehension through its own internal logic. The myths of old are abstracted, then internalized &lt;em&gt;into&lt;/em&gt; this individuated subject. This internalization is what Steiner identifies as the awakening of the “Intellectual” or “Mind Soul”. There is a specific layer of human being being developed here. The Indian cultural age is where the &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt;-ness was secured, the primal spiritual memory of a divine reality, or ultimate intelligibility/intelligence. The Persian and Egyptian culural ages externalized this “that” into forces and images. Now in this age, the soul turns this inward to create a new instrument: the individual intellect/intelligence capable of abstract thought. The “I”, or ego, begins to crystallize within the soul and no longer needs to receive truth from the outside. It strives to discover truth from within itself using logic and philosophy. Socrates is important here, since now that knowledge is not revealed through omens and oracles, it becomes elicited through subjectivity. Marked by the emergence of the Socratic method, where the subject looks outwards towards other subjects to see the correspondence between what is said and the internal coherence found within the ego, and the logical deduction of Aristotle (seen through the syllogism), what you find isn’t a total departure from reality. Instead, this moment serves as a translation of totality into conceptual form, where consciousness needs to grasp the relationship between the internal subjective act of thought, to “being”. In other words, the spirit descends into full self-conscious individuality, but at the cost of the split between the subject and object in its philosophic form, the form relevant for this age of consciousness/intelligibility. For the first time, man stood clearly as a thinking subject over against a world of objects to be known. Socrates asks “what is the good life” rather than asking “what do the Gods will?”. Plato asks, &amp;ldquo;Is the pious loved by the gods because it is pious, or is it pious because it is loved by the gods?”. Answers to these questions are then sought within human reason because they cannot be answered in a way which generates inward necessity with myths and stories. And so, Plato’s Forms are intelligible to us as this new layer of man grasping the spiritual world in the mode of thought, rather than image or myth. What was once known as the Egyptian God &lt;em&gt;Ma’at&lt;/em&gt; (cosmic order/truth) has turned into Plato’s Form of Justice, the abstract ideal discovered by mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The very act of elevating the subjective “I” as the seat of reason created a chasm between the inner world of thought, and the outer world of being. For centuries, this split would be bridged by a shared belief in the divinely ordered cosmos in Medieval Scholasticism, whose goal was to reconcile this new capability of thought by differentiated subjects, and (the yet to be realized broadly transformative force) of faith. However, this bridge was temporary. The isolated sovereign “I” that Greece had midwifed would, in a later time, wake up to find itself truly alone, staring into the void at a silent and mechanical universe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/a/a8/Nighthawks_by_Edward_Hopper_1942.jpg"
loading="lazy"
alt="Nighthawks"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nighthawks&lt;/em&gt;, by Edward Hopper&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;br&gt;This painting is famous for being the visual of modern alienation. Figures are isolated in a sterile, geometric space, separated from each other, and the dark void of the outside street. The disenchanted world of the Consciousness Soul is captured with clarity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id="germanic-anglo"&gt;Germanic-Anglo
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The pivot into a mechanical universe is not sudden, it was the logical culmination of the Greco-Roman project. The individual “I” which was nurtured through the Christian Middle Ages with its focus on individual salvation and conscience, arrived at its inheritance in the Germanic-Anglo cultural age, or the modern world. What changes here is not the existence of the “I”, but self-awareness and the relationship to the world that this “I” has. In the Greco-Roman world, the “I” was born and begins to discover its power to reason about the world, in the same way that a baby recognizes that its hand is its own, and begins to play with it, moving it about and seeing the limits of what it can do. The Germanic-Anglo world finds the “I” turning its analytic gaze back onto &lt;em&gt;itself&lt;/em&gt; and upon the world it has systematically disenchanted. This is what Steiner would call the “Consciousness Soul”, where the ego becomes fully conscious of its dilemma - that is, being separate from the world. In Gebser’s terms, it is the deficient mode of the Mental structure. The radical subject-object duality leads to alienation and analysis-for-its-own sake, or fragmentation. Descartes’ Cogito is what identifies the pivot found in this moment. In exclaiming “I think, therefore I am”, the thinking self establishes itself as the only certainty. The entire external world, even the body, becomes a potential illusion. This is the “I” declaring at once its total independence, and its loneliness. Likewise, &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt; individuate. Hyper-individuated consciousness can be said to be the engine of the Scientific Revolution, since in its very goal of mastering nature through the tools provided by the “I” (mathematics and modern philosophy), it was professing the struggle of rebuilding a world of meaning from its solitary existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intelligibility of this kind reaches its culmination in the project of Hegel, who, starting from the Platonic &lt;em&gt;Idea&lt;/em&gt;, produced the grandiose completion of philosophy in his system of Absolute Idealism. It was the most heroic modern attempt to heal the subject-object split that this age produced. From the immediate certainty of thought (the legacy of Descartes and Kant), Hegel wanted to show how the &lt;em&gt;ultimate&lt;/em&gt; intelligibility (Geist, or Spirit) logically unfolds through history and consciousness, reconciling subject and object, or man and the world in one grand structure, or in other words, showing how thought grasps itself and what follows from this development. He concludes that the Cartesian &lt;em&gt;cogito’s&lt;/em&gt; assertion of the immediate identity of thought and being ends up losing both. The Cartesian &lt;em&gt;cogito&lt;/em&gt; establishes only an abstract, empty identity between thought and being, which fails to encompass any real content. This creates an irreducible dualism between the thinking substance and extended matter. Ironically, by defining matter purely through the intellectual property of extension, Descartes’ “materialism” ends up portraying matter as a rarefied product of thought, thereby spiritualizing it. As for Kant, I have written in depth about the transition from Kant to Hegel &lt;a class="link" href="https://goddesscameo.github.io/p/from-hegel-to-steiner/#the-peaks-and-valleys-of-german-idealism" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. While not exactly being the culmination of &lt;em&gt;Greek&lt;/em&gt; thought, Hegel’s project was the ending of the modern mind’s struggle in overcoming isolation. In this way, the solution that is Hegel’s system is instead a symptom of the very crisis it&amp;rsquo;s trying to solve. Absolutely, it is worthy of study, if not for historical reasons, then because of the strength of thought it develops in oneself if taking his project seriously. But as the proposed ultimate intelligibility of the world, it is in reality the most sophisticated and developed &lt;em&gt;expression&lt;/em&gt; of the problem, masquerading as its solution. The drive to unify everything into a single &lt;em&gt;rational&lt;/em&gt; structure is the ultimate expression of the modern, sovereign “I”, asserting its intellectual dominion over all reality. This is the philosophical equivalent of the Scientific Revolution’s mission statement of mastering nature through reason, just applied to history and Ideality. His system is a staggeringly intricate, and at times beautiful, map of a territory, trying to convince us that the map &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; the territory. In being the expression of the isolated modern intellect, it tries to generate cosmic meaning from its own logical operations after failing to find the necessity/intelligibility in the given myths and stories of the previous age (what he would call truth in representational form, or religion, which bears genuine content, but also of which the thinking subject cannot accept as valid since its necessity is not produced immanently by reason, thereby leaving the subject-object divided). Likewise, the meaning produced from the system, for example the &lt;em&gt;concept&lt;/em&gt; of life, is a shadow over the living reality of life, rather than directly receiving the meaning from the object in question, while grasping it internally as necessary and true. As a result, all claims from philosophy, with Hegel&amp;rsquo;s system of Absolute Idealism in mind, about the world end up being coincidental. Insofar as the structure of reason is true, there is a direct correlate in the world. But this does not equate to truly unifying the subject and object.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having pushed the qualitative project of this sovereign “I” to its absolute limit, Hegel’s system did not resolve modern alienation. Almost immediately, the reaction to his system was followed by attitudes that dismantled the qualitative dimension. In the wake of Hegel, two attitudes emerged that cleared the ground for the quantification of totality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="materialism"&gt;Materialism
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first was the objectification of the source, or subject. Thinkers like Ludwig Feuerbach and the young Karl Marx held that the “I” is no longer the source of meaning (Spirit) in thought, but rather a node within a larger web. Feuerbach’s claim is that Hegel’s Spirit is a projected &lt;em&gt;human&lt;/em&gt; essence. The “I” is not the vehicle of cosmic reason, it is a being which is natural and sensuous. This reaction dragged the “I” down from the realm of pure thought into the sensuous world of biology and psychology - into the world of empirical study. Marx similarly said the “I” is not defined by consciousness, but by social relations and material praxis. The thinking subject is a product of economic and historical forces, in effect, making the “I” &lt;em&gt;itself&lt;/em&gt; an effect within an analyzable system of objects. It is important to recognize that the “materialist inversion” is the shadow of the Cartesian moment. Where Descartes’ isolated &lt;em&gt;cogito&lt;/em&gt; declared: “I think, therefore I am” and secured the thinking self as the only certainty, the “materialist inversion” proclaims: “I labor, therefore we transform”. It actually &lt;em&gt;accepts&lt;/em&gt; the &lt;em&gt;cogito’s&lt;/em&gt; declaration of independence from a mythic cosmos, but reject’s its loneliness. It claims that the “I” is not a singular existence, but is in fact a node in a collective, laboring human species-being. This inversion doesn’t solve the subject-object split, instead it radicalizes the Cartesian instance of domination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Slavoj Žižek observes in the Soviet ethos, the materialist project becomes “man’s domination over nature” (I could be misattributing this to him, although I think it’s fair to characterize the Soviet ethos this way). The Cartesian “I,” which sought to master nature (or the world) through mathematics, is collectivized into a historical “we” that seeks to master nature through industry and science through the social substance known as the Soviet people. In shifting the goal from individual certainty to collective control, intelligibility is no longer about finding meaning in the world, but about extracting utility from it. The qualitative “I” that contemplated and participated is replaced by the quantitative “human factor” that must be optimized and engineered. The “materialist inversion” completes the severance initiated by Descartes. It takes the sovereign subject and embeds it within a material system that the subject is meant to dominate, turning the gaze of analysis outward and downward onto the very conditions of its own existence. A dualism is at play here. The “I” becomes both the agent of domination, and a unit within the dominable field. This duality is exactly what makes the “I” ripe for measurement. To dominate nature efficiently, you must first calibrate the instrument.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The materialist inversion, while some claim it to be radical, did not necessarily lead to the positivist world that gave birth to the modern concept of intelligence. By embedding the “I” within a historical struggle or sensuous human essence, it preserved the qualitative dimension, or a form of telos for man. Whether it be the liberation of the species, or the realization of man’s potential. Intelligence here is still &lt;em&gt;intelligible&lt;/em&gt; as praxis, taking the form of an engagement with the world inseparable from the enabling conditions which the “I” actualizes itself through. Meaning, the exclusive &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;-ness of will, community, and historical context. One could not isolate and score this on a sheet, since its value was in its very application toward collective and social ends. It can be rightly said then, that this materialist inversion presaged intelligence becoming a commodity of force in the world. It presaged the Ahrimanic impulse, the drive toward absolute immanence, materialism, and mechanistic dominion over the world. However, the materialist inversion was an impulse still tempered, no matter how faintly, by a humanistic purpose. And so the “I” was an object of science, but in the service of the social substance, and as a result, a grand transformation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="positivism"&gt;Positivism
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;The qualities of the “I” can now be studied as objects. This is an important precondition for measurement. The second reaction to Hegel was the &lt;em&gt;positivist&lt;/em&gt; one. Rather than objectifying the “I” from the outside, there is a dissolving involved of its core &lt;em&gt;qualitative&lt;/em&gt; experience as a legitimate category of knowledge. The reaction is essentially: “Hegel wasn’t wrong, just meaningless!”. Positivists claim his project is a result of misusing language, or a product of metaphysical confusion. This attitude is also home to the attitude of thinkers who assume that because they cannot understand something, their lack of understanding constitutes the unintelligibility of that thing. The very fact that something &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; makes it intelligible. Nevertheless, according to the positivist, statements about “Spirit”, “the meaning of history”, and even “subjective truth” are completely nonsensical. Early Wittgenstein, in his Tractatus Logico-Philosophicus, didn’t argue with Hegel, the action taken was drawing a boundary limit. Propositions could only picture states of affairs in the world. Everything else, everything ideal, like ethics, aesthetics, the meaning of life, and the nature of the “I” was unspeakable. It belongs to a category known as mystical. Sure, it could be &lt;em&gt;shown&lt;/em&gt; how one lived, but it could not be &lt;em&gt;said&lt;/em&gt; in any logically meaningful proposition and likewise communicated intelligibly. It’s not quite a critique, more like a juvenile rejection of accepting that the domain of qualitative subjective experience is a field of legitimate knowledge. Hence there can be no private language, according to early Wittgenstein. Bertrand Russell and the Vienna Circle turned this into a ruthless program known as the “verifiability principle”. A statement under this program could only be meaningful to a subject only if it is either analytic (true by definition, such as logic or math), or empirically verifiable. It was touted as a guillotine for concepts. Under this guillotine, the head of Hegel’s Spirit rolls, as do all concepts like “the good”, the “beautiful”, and paradoxically, the “I”. Supposedly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This principle of “verificationism” is perhaps the ultimate expression of vapidity. Ignoring historical and logical preconditions, it fails its own test. If only analytic or empirically verifiable statements are meaningful, then it itself, being neither analytic nor empirically verifiable, stands as a decree about the nature of meaning which lacks meaning altogether &lt;em&gt;on its own account&lt;/em&gt;. In fact, rather than refuting Hegel, it embodies the very same alienation that his philosophy aimed to overcome. Reason in this attitude becomes so terrified of reality, ambiguity, and the world, that it confines itself to a self-made cell of tautologies and instrument-readings, and call this the entire world. No, it doesn’t prove that qualitative experience is unreal. All it proves is that it is incapable of making it intelligible. After all, near the end of his life, AJ Ayer recognized this very critical blow, and admitted that he wasted his life on the movement, below @33:54:
&lt;div class="video-wrapper"&gt;
&lt;iframe loading="lazy"
src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/S6_Vy-Uzwzc"
allowfullscreen
title="YouTube Video"
&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-modern-understanding-of-intelligence"&gt;The Modern Understanding of Intelligence
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;What remained after the positivist reaction to the situation the “I” found itself in, after declaring the qualitative dimension of the “I” unspeakable, was a ghost. The living, meaning-seeking subject is gone, and what remained in its place was the “I” as a logical-grammatical placeholder in the level of ideality. The “I” is only a bundle of sense data and set of behavioral dispositions. Intelligence, stripped of meaning and participation, was redefined as the sterilized functional capacity for valid logical manipulation and efficient problem-solving. No longer was it a faculty for rendering the world intelligible, but a kind of processing engine which navigates rule-bound systems. The operative definition of intelligence is now “abstracted, pure cognitive processing power”. Now it is not the soul’s capacity to render a meaningful cosmos intelligible, nor is it the mind’s participation in something intelligible. Stripped of all content, this redefinition is the functional efficiency of a biological logic-machine. “Solve for x, complete this series, manipulate these abstract relations”. This intelligence is computational and decontextualized. The value lies in generating correct outputs from defined inputs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This conceptual vacuum created an irresistible demand. If intelligence is a generic processing power, then it must be measurable and rank-able. The bureaucratic and scientific mindset, fathered by a positivistic spirit, simply can’t sit aside and &lt;em&gt;let&lt;/em&gt; a variable called intelligence remain a qualitative mystery, and so, an abstract model requires a concrete metric. This metric arrives in the form of the IQ test as an instrument to fulfil the modern understanding of intelligence. It is the applied, institutionalized truth of logical positivism. The test design perfectly mirrors the definition. The only skills exclusively measured are analytical skill and empirical pattern recognition, which are the very same competencies the positivist “I” was said to possess. Morality, out-of-the-box creativity (such as test takers. What if you are smarter than the test makers, can a test accurately capture this?), embodied wisdom, and more are completely left to the wayside. An assessment is not made of how one &lt;em&gt;reads between the self and the world&lt;/em&gt;, all we have left is a standardized performance review of a supposed isolated cognitive processor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The test’s history certainly confirms its role as an applied ideology. Alfred Binet developed early scales as a practical, &lt;em&gt;via negativa&lt;/em&gt; tool to identify educational need. However, it was successors like Lewis Terman in America, infused with eugenic ideology, and positivist spirit, who transformed it into the &lt;em&gt;via positiva&lt;/em&gt; metric we recognize today. Such successors operationalized the abstract notion of general processing power (g) into a single score, claiming to represent innate, hierarchically distributed intellectual worth. In doing so, the foundational error of the test was established: the bankruptcy of conceptual value. With its single-scored nature creating a self-justifying loop, intelligence was defined as what the test measures, and the test was hailed as the measure of intelligence. The circular logic on display was grafted onto a statistical fallacy, treating the mind’s complexity as a linear trait distributable along a bell curve. The resulting test became the key tool for rationalizing educational tracking, immigration policy, social triage, social hierarchy, and so on and so forth, measuring little more than the proxy skills of test-taking conformity and abstract puzzle solving. These are the very aptitudes of the bureaucrat and clerk, not the visionary or the sage. Thus, the modern IQ test is the bureaucratic apotheosis of the eviscerated modern “I”. It is the ultimate artifact of a consciousness that, having lost the world and then annihilated its own qualitative interior, could conceive of nothing more meaningful than to assign itself a number. What we have before us, is a quantitative monument built upon the buried grave of qualitative intelligence. In this, it stands as the perfect, pathetic shrine of our age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Truly, it can be said that the &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; IQ test, the test which measures for intelligence, for how well one grasps intelligibility, is seeing through IQ test itself. To grasp it as a ritual for the modern age that reduces everything into Ahriman, into breakdown and quantification, is to pass the exam it is administering. In grasping that its numbers and patterns are a self-referential game, one demonstrates the very faculty the test cannot measure but is claiming to measure: the ability to read between the lines of a system or thing and discern its rules and non-immediate functions. The test rewards those who play by its rules. It satisfies the ego, and whole social environments are built upon it’s connotations. But it silently fails those who understand its irrelevance. The ultimate act of intelligence in the face of IQ is to perceive the boundaries of the instrument meant to contain intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/b/ba/M.O.D.O.K_%28Marvel_Comics_character%29.png"
loading="lazy"
alt="MODOK"
&gt;&lt;img src="https://encrypted-tbn0.gstatic.com/images?q=tbn:ANd9GcTI0f1YIwmMPq8SN8hWSJpBH8yMqwTIWJxghQ&amp;amp;s"
loading="lazy"
alt="Ariman"
&gt;&lt;img src="https://miro.medium.com/1*ydp9M7DT52mshFWkq38W1w.jpeg"
loading="lazy"
alt="Alien"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h1 id="ahrimanic-gallery"&gt;Ahrimanic Gallery
&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nerve-sense system is the bodily correlate of abstract, calculative thinking. Ahriman (depicted on the top right as a sculpture done by Rudolf Steiner) works by hypertrophying intellect while severing it from feeling and will. The enlarged head symbolizes consciousness becoming cold, detached, and mechanized, where thinking dominates the whole human being instead of serving an integrated spiritual life. The marvel character MODOK (depicted top left) visually embodies the Ahrimanic imbalance Steiner warns about: a hypertrophied head (abstract, calculating intellect) mechanically sustaining a diminished body, symbolizing intelligence as severed from the other activities of the ego/I. Grey aliens (depicted bottom) repeat the same. Enlarged heads signify hyper-intellect, while small hands and bodies indicate the atrophy of will and feeling under a one-sided dominance of cognition. Note: this is not a claim that the above figures &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; Ahrimanic (well, aside from Ahriman of course), it is only to point out the forms they take express an imaginary coherence which signify certain relations between intellect, other activities of the ego, and embodiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="multiplicity-band-aid"&gt;Multiplicity Band-Aid
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Faced with the devastating inadequacy of the monolith IQ score, for example its inability to capture creativity, wisdom, social skills, and morality, the modern paradigm does not reconsider its foundations. Instead, it performs the classic move of a failing ideology. It multiplies its errors and reproduces them. This is done by stepping back from the “one” score, and stating that in reality, there are multiple “scores” for the multiple “intelligences”. The retreat from the single “g” factor, to the theory of “multiple intelligences” is certainly not progress, it is the desperate attempt to preserve the core reductionist project of conceiving the mind as a quantifiable collection of measurable traits by fragmenting the trait of “intelligence” into more pieces when the original “concept” proves too elusive. There is a fundamental category error at play here. The domain/medium in which intelligence “operates” is mistaken for a distinct &lt;em&gt;type&lt;/em&gt; of intelligence. This is as ludicrous as saying there is a “hammering” intelligence, and a “sawing” intelligence, rather than the recognizing a source in both actions as a unitary mechanical understanding applied to different tools. The manifestation of a faculty is not a separate faculty, and so listing &lt;em&gt;applications&lt;/em&gt; of intelligence and pretending that these are in fact a result of the theory of the applicator is empty posturing. Not entirely empty, since it perfectly mirrors the fragmented, dissociated, consciousness of the modern age at its endpoint. Having first shattered the living world into dead matter, and then shattered the living subject into a solitary intellect, it now shatters intellect itself into a checklist of intellects. Hyper-specialization of this kind is the bureaucratic mind’s last refuge in the face of the problem of quality. If you can’t measure the whole, then you subdivide it until you can measure the parts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where we must re-assert the unitary character of intelligence, grounded in our initial exploration of the concept. Intelligence is not six or seven different things. It is the &lt;em&gt;singular&lt;/em&gt; core capacity to discern. What varies is not the intelligence, but the field in which it reads (math, social scenarios, kinesthetic), the tools it uses (logic, ideally empathy, rhythm/awareness of the body), and the &lt;em&gt;familiarity&lt;/em&gt; one has with the previous two. The musician who perceives harmonic tension, and the mathematician discerning a numeric contradiction are employing fundamentally the same faculty of intelligence. The difference lies in the pattern and the mediums. Furthermore, the fragmentation is not benign. It reproduces and diffuses the same normative implication that IQ, with the monolithic “g”, did. The single-value model created a blunt hierarchy of intelligence. “&lt;em&gt;If&lt;/em&gt; there are higher and lower intelligences, then it necessarily follows that individuals with higher intelligences should be valued”, whatever that means. Operationally, it acted (and continues to act) as a perfect tautology for those who wish to take its result and vindicate this or that theory of man and intelligence. In assuming a taxonomy of general cognitive worth (“g”) and designing puzzles to isolate and measure it, it uses the resulting scores as proof that such a taxonomy is real, mistaking its operational definition for a discovery about nature. The multiple-intelligences model, in response, creates a sprawling map of ranked categories. All it does is expand this process. It creates a taxonomy of separate mental modules, then designs domain-specific tasks to measure them. After that, it uses these results to validate the initial compartmentalization. In both cases, the test’s designs predetermine its conclusion. The underlying impulse remains unchanged, this being the compulsion to sort, label, then compare. Whether claiming a group excels in “mathematical” intelligence or lacks in “spatial” intelligence, the framework still traffics in the implication of normativity. It provides a more nuanced, albeit culturally sensitive, lexicon for that same old project of cataloguing human worth by type. This is the more polite 21st century face of the much older logic which believes that human minds can be definitively taxonomized, and that these taxonomies justify social and educational destiny. Generalities certainly do exist, but only as the result of &lt;em&gt;process&lt;/em&gt;. It is never a revelation of innate type. The observation that populations exposed to generations of colonialism, resource deprivation, and the deliberate destruction of their own cultural-linguistic frameworks might, and generally tend to do, perform differently on tests designed by and for another population group &lt;em&gt;even within&lt;/em&gt; the same ethnicity (say for example an educated class versus a working class which does not have the same opportunity for education or resources), let alone between different cultures. At this point, the IQ test is a number which reflects the culture and access to resources one’s parents have. For example, to look at the lower average scores of Haitian and Somali populations and conclude something about “African intelligence” is to commit the gravest error of the Ahrimanic paradigm. The effect is confused for the cause. The cause is not a cognitive deficiency, the cause is the legacy of material dispossession, lack of education, and cultural disorientation. These generalities, far from vindicating a taxonomy of racial or ethnic intellectual worth, should be read as indictments of the very systems (colonial, economic, and now psychometric) that created the conditions for the disparity and then designed the instrument to measure its consequence as if they were its origins. To see the score and believe in something like this is to be fooled by the most insidious of self-fulfilling prophecies and out oneself as not having the capacity to make the IQ test intelligible to themselves. In other words, it is the sign of an unintelligent person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-future-of-intelligence"&gt;The Future of Intelligence
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://smarthistory.org/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/cezannethumb-870x659.jpg"
loading="lazy"
alt="cezanne"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mont Sainte-Victoire series by Paul Cézanne&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;br&gt; Cézanne here is painting the act of perception itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sovereign “I”, or the Consciousness Soul as Steiner would call it, is left analyzing a disenchanted world, leading to alienation as well as this understanding of what constitutes “intelligence”. If the modern error is to substitute the abstract metric for the living faculty, then any path forward must return to the act itself. The solution to the IQ paradigm, this current understanding of intelligence, is certainly not to design more abstract tests. It lies not in a refinement of metrics or further retreat into positivism. The answer is to remove proxy altogether. We must stop trying to simulate intelligence in a vacuum and instead test it &lt;em&gt;in situ&lt;/em&gt; by evaluating the performance of the action that constitutes it. This means shifting our focus from the disembodied skill of “pattern recognition” to the more concrete act of, for example, deciphering a historical text’s latent causes, or diagnosing a complex system. Instead of attempting to measure “abstract reasoning” through logic puzzles, the test of abstract thinking would be engaging in the works of Hegel, where &lt;em&gt;intelligence&lt;/em&gt;, or intelligibility is demonstrated in the faithful following of thought in abstract thought. In such a framework, assessment almost becomes inseparable from education and practice. You’d never measure a surgeons&amp;rsquo; intelligence with a paper quiz on anatomy (although I’d hope they know their anatomy). The assessment is done by observing it in the theater and viewing how the surgeon integrates knowledge and sensorimotor skills, with on-the-fly Judgment under pressure. Nor would you measure the capability of a basketball player in playing basketball with their squat and push-up limits. You would assess them by &lt;em&gt;doing&lt;/em&gt; the activity of interacting with a ball. Intelligence as being the capacity to make things intelligible can only be authentically evaluated when it is engaged in the actual work of rendering a real context and content intelligible. The move from abstracted metric to enaction is the first step out of Ahriman’s cage of quantification, since it respects intelligence for what it is as a relational event.
What the future of intelligence necessarily requires is to go beyond the paradigm of this kind of measurement altogether and into a comprehensive reintegration. Firstly, a healing of the subject-object split that defines modern consciousness is needed. The individuated “I” (subject), having fully won its sovereignty, must freely choose to reunite with the world (object) in partnership. The goal is to retain the modern ego’s clarity and analytical power, while shedding its alienation from the world and thereby regaining a participatory, living connection to the world. In the future, intelligence will no longer be a number on a sheet, it will be recognized once against as a quality of relationship manifest in action and creation. The future of intelligence advances to what Rudolf Steiner foresaw as the next stage of consciousness: the development of the spirit-self. In the future, the status of the conscious “I” transforms. Having fully secured its individuality and analytical power through the modern “consciousness soul”, it will now turn these capacities outward with a new intention.
The “I” will not experience itself as a spectator locked inside a skull, observing a dead, mechanical, world outside its grasp. Through disciplined inner development, consciousness can &lt;em&gt;and will&lt;/em&gt; evolve to perceive the living ideas and spiritual forces actively shaping the world. In this act of perception, there is a transcendence of the passive observation of sense-certainty. It begins with meticulous phenomenological attention to the object. Whether it be a plant or a social dynamic, it does not matter, what matters is not interpreting the thing in front of you as a dead thing, but as a dynamic appearance. The observer then actively engages in a process of participatory thinking, striving to trace the living idea, or spiritual form, manifesting through the phenomenon. One does not impose external theory here. Through a disciplined imagination (which has a specific definition for Steiner), one follows the logic of the object’s own becoming. The questions asked are not along the lines of “what causes it?”, they are asking along the lines of “What is its inherent necessity? What spiritual form reveals itself as this particular phenomenal form?”. In doing so, the thinker’s consciousness aligns with the generative principle of the object. The subject no longer stands in opposition to a foreign object. By thinking the object&amp;rsquo;s own formative reality from within, the act of perception becomes the very medium in which the object’s essentiality is realized. The subject-object split is healed in this activity. The subject’s perceiving &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; the object’s self-disclosure. Thus, a mental illness is not reduced to neural correlates, but understood as a coherent, albeit pathological, shape of meaning and living experience, whose necessity can be discerned in its own terms. True intelligence, now and in the next age, is the capacity for this kind of perception, where the mode of intelligibility consciousness takes is characterized by uniting with the intelligible form in the act of its apprehension, thereby finding the self back into the world, where it never really left.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our long examination of intelligence has concluded with a reorientation of an old definition. We traced the phantom of our modern intelligence from its origins as an act of making things intelligible to us, to its imprisonment as a quantified score, a journey which mirrors consciousness’s own evolution into the alienated sovereign “I”. IQ, in addition to being a flawed metric, is the perfect character of this deeper spiritual crisis. It is an artifact of a consciousness that has disenchanted the world, and now, in its loneliness, can conceive of no higher purpose than assigning itself an empty label. However, as the crisis reveals a disease, it also reveals a cure. The future of intelligence calls us not to invent a new test or metric, but to undertake a new kind of literacy that renders ourselves intelligible to a universe that is, and always has been, profoundly intelligible. It invites us to step into dialogue with the world, where the most intelligent thing you can do is participate in a mutual revelation of meaning.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>